There's hundreds of directions you can
go uh in 3D if you want to take logos
and bring them to life because at the
end of the day we're playing with
geometry. It's just in the shape of a
logo. But this week I wanted to take six
ideas and make something really cool
with them. Ended up making some really
cool animations and a couple still
images. So, what I want to do today is
show you the bones, the concept of how
to do those processes in Blender and
just show you enough to where you can
take them and then make them your own
with your own ideas and how to take
those ideas and go further with them
with your own creativity. The first
concept is taking your geometry,
converting it to a volume so that you
can then displace it in really cool ways
that goes beyond your typical
displacement modifier. and then we're
going to convert it back into geometry
so that you can add materials, lighting,
anything you want to do it past that.
The second one is conceptually very
simple. You're taking just an image of
your logo, black and white, throwing it
in Blender, and manipulating it with
procedural textures to create this
transitioning morphing effect with
anything you want to do. It's very
powerful, but very simple to execute.
This might be my favorite one. Uh, but
we're taking a logo and able to control
the emission outwards and inwards
independently to make a really cool
animation. Fourth concept is just being
able to fill the inside of your logo
with objects. I'm going to show you two
methods. One that helps you fill it
really well. Another method that allows
you some space to animate those points.
Then I'm going to show you how to take
the black and white image of a logo, use
it as a mask in geometry node. So, we
can delete things, scale things, really
show you how to take an image, map it in
Geometry Nodes, and then you can take
your further Geometry Nodes knowledge to
do whatever you want under that idea.
And the last one, I'm going to show you
the quickest way to add fur to a logo
and make it look really good very, very
quickly. So, we're going to get into all
of those right now. Before that, I want
to let you guys know that there are six
completed step-by-step tutorials on all
of these concepts on my Patreon right
now. I get to slow down, show you each
one of these ideas in depth, and really
show you how to make something really
awesome by the end of them. If you want
to check that out, that is on my Patreon
today, and you can get a discount if you
subscribe annually. With that being
said, let's get into these concepts.
Okay, so concept one, taking geometry,
converting it to volumes, and being able
to displace and sort of manipulate it
that way. First, we are going to need
the SVG of a logo. Um, but what you'll
do is you just import and click on SVG.
And I'm going to grab the Blender logo.
So, we have the logo. First thing we
need to do is add some thickness to it.
Because it is currently a curve, you can
go ahead in the geometry section and
extrude that. And this is all we're
going to need to do. And I'm just going
to go ahead and convert it to a mesh.
Now, we have real geometry. Now, I'm
going to hide that. And the first step
to converting this into a volume is in
the volume settings, go ahead and create
an empty. And that is going to give you
a subset of modifiers you now have
access to. We can search up a mesh to
volume node and then you can grab that
logo and you can start to see it show
up. You bring up that density and then
you can bring up that voxil amount. We
now have a volume version of the logo
and if you are in cycles you quite
literally have now a volume version of
this logo. Like already this is a cool
concept. Now we're going to get a volume
displace. So search that up. Volume
displace. This is going to allow you to
now throw textures on this just like a
displacement texture. So, we'll go into
the textures and I'm going to do
distorted noise. And we now have this.
Again, if we pop back into cycles, it's
pretty cool. Now, keep in mind your
voxil amount. I have it at 500, which is
way too much just to show you guys
what's going on. Let me just pop it down
to 200. We can go ahead and play with
that size. The strength is quite a
lot right now. So, we'll maybe bring it
down to something like this. Now what I
can do is convert it back to geometry.
So what we'll do is we'll just add a
geometry nodes modifier and then open
that up and then there is a volume to
mesh node. Volume to mesh that is going
to convert it back. It looks pretty
insane. We can fix that with a set shade
smooth node. And then you can see it's
still kind of steppy if that's a proper
word. I'm gonna bring my voxil amount to
like 400. You could see that. I think
it's cool, but it's not on purpose. So,
you just bring that threshold up. Then
you can head back to the texture and
start to just play with some stuff. Uh I
would play with the contrast
specifically cuz I want to get these
holes in uh the scene. And then you can
maybe bring that size up. And now you
have something really really wild. I
find this volumeing and then texturing
uh to be very stable. And I really
really like this method. And you can
throw any texture within this on that.
So you can even mix them. We'll do maybe
do a cell noise. And now we have this
very quickly. And it's it's pretty
stable. You have like weird things like
this, but you can work with it. But that
is how you can create something really
really cool very quickly. Uh with
volumes. For this next thing, you are
going to need a black and white image of
your logo. Something like this. I'm
going to use uh the Nike logo. Um, but
get a PNG or JPEG of a black and white
image. Um, what we'll do now is I'm
going to go ahead on image mesh plane
and I'm going to grab my logo. So, I'm
going to scale it up and we're going to
open up a shader window and I'm going to
look at this in Eevee. So, now we have
this and we have a couple things that we
can do here. So, I'm just going to go
ahead and sever these connections. Give
myself an emission of 10 and we're going
to plug this guy right into color. And
off the bat, we need to invert it. So,
first you have some ugliness right
there. You can fix
that with a color ramp set to constant.
That's going to fix that weird ugliness.
Can't explain it, but that is the case.
So, here's what we can do. Go ahead and
get a mapping setup. Just a mapping node
and a texture coordinate. And we are
going to go ahead and throw a texture on
here. I'm going to use the Gabber
texture because I've never actually used
it on the YouTube channel yet. and it's
going to give you something really cool
like this. So now we've completely lost
the logo. So now I'm going to go ahead
and get in a mix color node to create a
bypass. So we can just say how much of
this texture are we actually wanting um
to see. So this is a really really cool
texture. Again, one that I've not talked
about, but you can change the
orientation to actually fit the shape of
the Nike logo. So when we morph it in,
it
actually makes more sense in terms of
this transition. Uh there's a lot of
really really cool things that you can
do uh with this texture. But look at
that. All we have to do is animate this
in. So let's go ahead. So I'm going to
go ahead and set up my camera just to
have most of the logo. I really like the
composition of cutting off part of the
logo. I think it looks really, really,
really cool. And then what I'm going to
do now is because we have kind of a high
emission, we can go into the
compositing right here. I'm going just
click use node and get a glare node. Set
it to bloom. And then we can go back to
layout. And I'm just going to go say
always. And then we can just make it
glow a little bit. And then you can
change the color of your logo here. Nike
does love red. So we'll do that. And
then all we have to do is just
animate this factor to whatever extent
you want it to start. Maybe something
like that looks really cool. So I'm
going to go ahead. You'll just hit I on
the factor. Go to maybe 120. Bring it
over. And then we can
enjoy
this. Just like that. And that is how
you create logos and morph them with
textures. This is my favorite animation
of all of them. yet it's probably one of
the most simple ways to execute um this
idea. So, let me show you how to do it.
So, just like always, we're going to
start with the SVG of our logo. What I'm
going to do is I'm just going to pull
off uh the geometry and we're just going
to extrude it so we have these nice
walls. And then I'm going to go ahead
and get a plane. So, if I go to the very
top and I hop into cycles, you can see
our logo and we'll add a material and
tell it to be emissive. So, off the bat,
we have something pretty cool and very,
very simple. We can even go ahead and
add some color to it. But, if I take
this logo and I duplicate it, we can go
back into the curve settings and right
here on offset, we can get another one
and just bring it in a little bit. So,
that's going to allow something really,
really cool to happen. So if we go back
to the top, I could take this texture.
We can now just maybe make it black and
now it limits. Now it's the only the
inner
texture that is creating emission and
it's blocking the other one. Or we can
do the opposite. We can just bring that
in and now it's just a texture on the
outside. But here is where we can make
it look really, really awesome. And then
if we head to the shader editor, I'm
going to go ahead and put the same
material on both of them just to make my
life easy. And let's plug a texture into
the emission with a color ramp. So we
have a noise texture plugged into this.
So now if we make it
4D, you can have a lot of fun with this.
Say bring the detail down, bring the
scale up, and you can do something
really awesome. So say we're going to
put this over to
BPLine. I'm going to add another black
just to crunch in the black portions.
I'm going to make this red.
I'm going to make another one a deep
blue so that we can just have a nice red
highlight. Then we'll bring the strength
up pretty good. And so now we
have we have
this. But here is the really really cool
part. I'm going to go ahead and click on
the inner
material, duplicate it so it's
different, and maybe make the in the
maybe make the texture on the inside
darker and the texture on the outside a
lot brighter. You can now independently
control each texture. And you can
animate the speeds and the directions of
those at different speeds, giving them a
really, really cool look. And because
it's the logo, it stays to the logo and
you have something really, really cool
and honestly very beautiful, especially
with the colors you can pick. You can
add a glare node. It's incredibly
simple. U but as long as you have access
to using the text tool or using curves
and you can bring in one of those logos.
It's very simple and it's awesome. So,
there's a lot of ideas that might lead
you to wanting to fill the inside of
your logo with objects. So, I'm going to
show you two very similar methods on how
to get objects filled. a different
method that's going to allow you to
animate the objects, but both have their
kind of pros and cons. All right, so I
have my logo. What I'm gonna do is open
up a geometry nodes window. And we are
going to be using geometry nodes to
create this effect. So if we click new,
you can actually go ahead and convert
this into a volume like this. And you
can bring that voxal amount to kind of
smooth it and make it look really nice.
And then we can do a distribute points
in volume. And then you can just bring
that density up. And now you have the
shape of your logo. You can also just
use the points themselves as the object
and they will render out as just a round
ball. In this case, this is exactly what
I want. Go ahead and actually bring the
original back with a join geometry. And
then we can add materials to this so we
can actually appreciate it. So I'll just
add a
material. Make it
glass. And you can now see the inside of
your scene. And just bring up that
density a whole bunch. And now you have
your logo. The problem is if I want to
make these objects move around, they are
going to be shooting. I mean, you can
already see some of them are coming out.
And that's just going to be editing your
seed value to make sure they're all
inside of it. But if I want to actually
animate this, I can't. It's too They're
too close to the edge already. So, let
me show you something you can do
instead. I'm going to kill this node
tree. And what we'll do, so what I can
do is I can duplicate my logo. And then
I'm going to take the original one and
in the curve settings right here, you
can just bring that offset in just like
this. And also bring that extrude in. So
you now have a smaller, skinnier version
of the logo. We can go back to geometry
nodes. And if I pull that old node tree
back and delete the original. So now we
have a bunch of objects that we can then
if we get a set position and animate
these with a noise texture. We can now
take these guys and you can do
this with the original geometry. So now
you can actually take these particles,
bring them up a little bit and actually
animate objects inside of your logo. So
both of these methods do populate the
inside. though it's just not going to
feel full. But that is how the two
methods of populating the inside of a
logo. Staying on the geometry nodes
topic, you can actually use masks to
delete objects. You can use masks to
control geometry within geometry nodes
to have some really really cool options
with making interesting things using
masks, creating geometry in geometry
nodes. It's very, very powerful. Just
like earlier in the video, we are going
to need a black and white version of our
logo. I'm just going to start with a
grid in geometry nodes. I'm going to
scale it up and give it subdivisions of
80. The biggest obstacle to making this
work is mapping the logo properly. So,
let me show you how to do that. We're
going to do a we're going to go ahead
and convert this over to just regular
points so we can actually see the logo.
And then if you get a delete geometry,
that's going to say, "Hey, delete
points." We're going to go ahead and
throw an image texture right onto this
and grab our logo. So, we're going to
use the Blender logo. And you can see
some type of tiling is happening here.
So, we're going to go here from repeat
to clip. I only want one logo. And
typically, we'd want a mapping node. We
can't do that. We don't have a mapping
node, geometry nodes, but a mapping node
is just vector math. So, if we plug in a
position and add, you can see, okay, now
we can put this logo wherever we want.
And then a scale node is just going to
keep that logo exactly how we want it.
It's not going to stretch or squash it.
It's going to respect uh where it, you
know, how it wants to to look. So now we
have this. And then we can just go ahead
and invert this. Now we have a logo made
of points, which is awesome. Now we
could do whatever we want here. We could
go ahead and just instance a cube on
every single one of these points that we
have. Then you can use a noise texture
to actually animate the scale which can
look really really cool. And then now
you have something really really awesome
like pretty quick and you can use any
object you want. But now we're at the
shape of the logo. So you can so you
have a lot of data. So if you are
familiar with geometry nodes taking this
mapping a logo doing something really
cool on Patreon I was able to take this
add a sur add some surrounding objects
to it controlling that with the image
texture added a procedural wood material
to it. So the creative application to
just a little bit of this data in
geometry nodes, especially if you're
familiar with geometry nodes, can really
yield some really awesome things.
Another really cool thing could just be
getting like a curved circle and then
randomizing some of these objects. You
can do another delete geometry and just
do a random value boolean and then you
can just have maybe like some of these
disappearing to give you more of an
organic look. So now some of these
objects are missing and you can even use
a noise texture too if you want to
animate this look. So there's a lot of
really really effective uses of this
idea in geometry nodes, but having this
image texture really cool. Last thing
I'm going to show you is how to get a
logo very quickly to look like this
little furball. We're not going to go
really really in depth with this. If you
want to get in depth with this exact
process, Southern Shotty has an awesome
video that I highly recommend if you
want to really get into this. But I'm
going to show you the bones of how to
get some fur super fast. So I remshed
and smoothed the logo. I do want it to
be kind of nice and round looking like
something like this. And then I'm just
going to go convert it to a mesh. Now,
for this you need UVs. This actually
works quite well, but if you just hit U
and do a smart UV project and click
unwrap, you can actually see like not
bad in in this in this context. It
actually works very well. It's certainly
not perfect, but it works really well.
here. What we'll do is I'll just hit F3
and click on a quick fur. So now we have
this. If I go here to cycles, we we have
fur. So it's going to open up a bunch of
these modifiers. Really simply, this top
modifier is just going to control the
way that the individual hair looks in
terms of how big it is. You have your
shape, which is going to kind of play
with, oh, where is sort of the
skinniness. So it inverts it like that.
is I'm have a radius of
03. I want kind of a thicker guy. And
then maybe my max brings this down a
little bit, but honestly, we'll keep it
here. Maybe bring my max down a little
bit. This next modifier is going to
control how many hairs are going to show
up in your render and your viewport. So,
we have density here. So, what I'm going
to do is I'm going to do my viewport
amount of like 0.005
000 five and then I'm going to do a
density of I'm going to do like 80,000.
So now you'll notice in the render it's
full big hairy guy but this is the
viewport. So this allows you to look at
your edits in real time but already
immediately this looks awesome. This
next one plays with the overall noise
pattern that creates those waves and
shapes that you can see in this render.
You can see that it's a noise texture.
This next one, the frizz actually edits
the kind of a noise pattern on the
individual hair rather than the full
each individual hair. So I play with So
if I play with the shape on these hairs,
you'll notice it kind of straightens
them out. If I bring them down, it
frizzes them a little bit more. So I'm
going to play with the distance on the
frizz and make it
really kind of tangly, but it
also makes them bigger. And so now we
can head into the curve presets that
Blender very recently added. So if we go
here to the asset browser, I'm going to
go to the very
bottom and I'm going to want to get a
trim hair curves modifier. And what
that's going to do is trim the length
based on all those edits. And then what
I don't want is it to look like I took a
razor and just raise razored the top.
So, I'm going to get them the max length
I want them here. And then the random
offset will bring a couple of them down.
So, now it's a bit of a random look. And
this is what we have so far. Very
quickly, it looks really good. Of
course, if you want a little bit if you
want control over the material, we do
have a fur material right here. So, what
I would do is just go ahead and add that
fur material also to the base. That says
curve. That's our logo. We'll click back
on curves. And then we can just switch
this guy over to the shader editor. Make
sure you click use nodes. And you'll now
have access to adding materials to this.
So I'm going to make it really rough.
You can plug a noise texture into this
whole system like that. Let's see how
this looks in a final and we'll be
completely done. And here we have it. A
very quick furry logo. I showed you
about 10% of the controls here. There's
a lot more you can do with this, but I
wanted to show you the quickest way to
make it just look really nice and really
cool for ideiation reasons. And you can
check out that video from Southern
Shoddy uh to really take this further.
So, there you guys go. That is six
concepts that you can do kind of
hundreds of things with just those base
ideas on how to change logos. Of course,
logo and Blender just means geometry in
the shape of a logo. So, that's kind of
the way to look at it. You can sculpt,
you can weight paint, you can do so many
things with logos to really bring brands
to life and make them look awesome. And
as a graphic designer, this is my
favorite topic. So, hope you learned
some stuff. Again, if you want to check
out the extended full tutorials on each
of these concepts and making something
really cool with it, you can check that
out on my Patreon now. And you can get a
discount if you subscribe annually. And
I'll see you guys in the next