How's it going? So, in this tutorial, we
are going to be making this animation
right here. We're first going to be
taking a black and white image and we're
going to be using that as the way to
create the text in our animation. First,
we're going to take a grid and duplicate
points within that grid. Then, use that
image as the way to delete the points
when they are in the space of the text.
After that, we'll do some simple
displacement to animate all of those
points and use that same displacement to
provide color within those points. Then
we just need some simple lighting.
Animate the movement with a loop and
we'll be done. If you want to learn more
about particle systems and how to make
them look cooler, light them, animate
them, a lot of different ways to control
your particle systems within Geometry
Nodes, I just launched an entire series
on my Patreon dedicated to that theme.
So, if you want to learn more about
that, check out my Patreon in the
description along with all the other
content that I have on there. And you
can get a discount if you subscribe
annually. With that being said, let's
get into this tutorial. All right, we
are going to be using this image as the
mask in our animation. If you don't have
your own black and white image, you can
quite literally use any black and white
image you want. Um, on Patreon right
now, you can actually grab the
attachment for free. You don't need a
Patreon account. I'll link in the
description. Just download the
attachment and you can get this or
again, use any black and white image as
your mask and it does not need to be
this aspect ratio. So, just have some
type of mask image that you want to use
as the shape within your particle
system. Now, let's go ahead here in
Blender. I'm going to open up a brand
new window. I'm going go ahead and get a
plane. And up here, we're going to get a
geometry nodes editor and click new. So,
first let's go ahead and get a cube. So,
we'll go ahead cube be cube. Plug him
here. And let's go ahead and stretch him
to be uh to fill the space that we want
to have our text occupy. Something
around these lines. It really does not
need to be exact. And just about how
thick you want those particles to be as
well. Something like this. Now, what we
can do is convert this thing to a
volume. So, mesh to volume,
just like that. And then you can bring
up that density. You can bring up that
voxil amount. H, which is really isn't
that important. And then you can bring
up that density to make sure that the
volume is the same size as our cube. Now
what we can do is do a distribute points
in volume. So distribute points in
volume node. And then you could start to
bring up that density pretty quick. And
now we have a field of randomly placed
uh particles. So what I want to do now
is I'm hit shift A and get a plane. And
I just want this plane uh to be the
floor that is going to we can see uh
through the text. And so we can just
bring that grid
right at the very bottom of the
particles. So if you go here to cycles,
you'll be able to see particles and a
floor. And it's cool and it's great. And
you can actually hit this drop down up
here and click scene world scene lights.
And you don't have to add lighting right
now to be able to kind of see this and
appreciate it. Now that we've created
our particles, let's go ahead and use
our image to delete the particles that
are going to take up the space of the
text. So, what we're going to do is get
a
delete geometry node. Make sure it says
points, but that's default, so it should
say it. We're going to get a image
texture.
Plug this right here into selection and
go here and open up your image. So now
if you see some weird things happening,
just know that means uh your image is
working. You can see it kind of getting
tile uh tiled all over here. So right
over here, go from repeat to clip. And
then we're going to get a couple nodes.
You can kind of see it happening right
there. Um so that's where my image is
existing. It's too small. It's just not
what we want. So what I'm going to do is
to get a position node. And what we're
going to create is a texture coordinate.
um they we don't have a texture
coordinate uh in the same exact way that
we do in um in the shading workspace. So
we can build it though. So position just
is important to know. Hey, there's space
here. So we're going to get in a
vector math node. He is going to
represent position. So we'll plug him
there. Just the add. And then we're
going to go ahead and get in uh
duplicate him. Switch him over to
multiply. He is going to represent the
scale function in a texture coordinate.
and you can plug it there. So now bring
your multiply back to one. In fact, if
you just bring it up like that, you will
start to see it happening. And because
this is like a scale, it also means you
can stretch and squash. Now this is your
position. So you can bring and center
out this thing. Of course, right now we
just need to actually scale it up. Um so
it will start to stretch around um in a
way that you don't want as you're
playing around with it. So it is just
going to uh it's going to be a matter of
just massaging this image until it takes
the form however you want it to. So
something like
this. There are some more sort of
intricate ways to actually get it to
perfectly map. Um I'm not really I'm not
going to be that exact about it. So now
we have an image that deletes objects.
We can see look at that. It works. Now
the next thing I want to do is use
displacement to animate all these
particles. And that's where hierarchy is
going to be very important. If we add
our displacement here, which let's just
go ahead and I'm going to show you
what'll happen. If I do this, and then I
add my noise texture to my set position
node and I click normalize and add
color.
Where' our text go? Right, that's
because the action is happening after
the formation of the text. We need to
displace our particles before the
formation of the text, before the
function of the deleting. And so what we
need to do instead of putting set
position after, put it before. And that
is going to be the only thing we need to
do. So just go ahead, get a set position
node, go and get in a noise texture. And
we're going to plug color right into
offset. And notice, bring that detail
down. Bring that scale up. No matter
what we do and switch this over to 4D,
that text is staying put. And that is
exactly what we want. I'm going to go
ahead and I'm going to bring up the
scale of my uh
box just because I know um it's going to
be moving around quite a bit. So I'm
going to go ahead here to the top. I'm
hit shift A. Get a camera control alt0
and snap it to view.
And I want my
text to be like this. So now I know,
hey, the text needs to be centered out a
little bit. So, we'll go back to our
mapping nodes and say, "Hey,
stay in the middle." All right. Next is
the scale of our points. They're kind of
big. Um, particle systems, at least ones
like this, they tend to look better at
higher volumes and smaller scales. This
is just kind of glob and ugly. And so,
what we can do is get a set
point radius. And then you can start to
bring that down to maybe 0.02.
There we go. Very small. Which means
we just need to bring up the density
of our displacement. Now, here's one
thing that I want to change. Notice the
uh displacement is going to be on X, Y,
and the Z in terms of our uh set
position. I don't want that. I only want
the displacement to happen this way. I
don't want it to happen that way. I want
it to be perfectly flat. So, what we can
do here on the noise texture, make sure
you are unchecking normalize. And then
what we need to do is get a vector math
node. Set that to a multiply. And what
that's going to let us do is actually
not only play with the strength of the
displacement that we're giving it, which
will automatically make it really more
wiggly and more interesting and just a
little bit more fun to look at, but also
is going to say, "Hey, don't don't
displace it that way. Keep it on the
flat." Cuz that's going to help with the
effect that we're going for. And also
just lets us play with it on the X and
the Y. And then when we animate it, it
will look really, really cool. So now we
have this. You can play with uh the
radius of your objects if you want a
little bit more. To me, it's going to be
at a higher density. So what are we at?
180. Let's do like 600.
So that looks cool. Now, it's not going
to look quite as obvious until we start
adding colors. So, let's go ahead and
start to add some shading to this. But I
want this noise texture to influence the
colors that we're going to see on our
particles. So, what we can do is right
after the set point radius, get a set
material node right over here, we can
just go ahead and click new. He's just
called 001. We'll go ahead and grab 001.
And then we can get a
we can hit shift A and get a store named
attribute. I'm going to say C for color.
Everything's lagging a little bit, so
I'm just going to bring my density down
to like 300 for now.
And then we can just go ahead and take
this color, plug it right into value.
And now we have that. And we can switch
this guy over to the shader editor. I'm
going to go back here to the view. Let's
go ahead and grab that attribute. So, we
got attribute right here, C for color,
and let's plug color right into color.
So, now we have this. So, now let's go
ahead and get a color ramp and select uh
some really cool colors. So, we're going
to go ahead get this a color ramp. And a
fun little trick is I'm going to go
switch this over to a HSV, switch this
to far, and then this color just make it
red. It's going to create this big kind
of rainbow situation. And then once you
have that established, you can go get a
hue, saturation, value node and play
around with values until you start to
like the situation that you're in. This
is cool. I think we can run with this
one um for this tutorial. This looks
awesome. And then now we can just go
ahead back to the geometry nodes editor
and just see how it would look as final
density. So, what? 1,000. No, 600.
600 on the density. There we go. This is
how it would look as a final. Now, we're
not quite done yet. This bottom color, I
do want to go ahead and select that. So,
I'm just going to click on the bottom um
t that's geometry notes. We'll just go
over here and then say make it kind of
like that yellow that we're getting
beneath. That'll kind of keep everything
cohesive. You can even make it, you
know, like a light purple if you want.
uh just kind of keeping it in the
family. You can even make it emissive.
Uh but in this case, we're just going to
keep it uh like this so it's nice and
readable. Now, for lighting, uh with
shots like this, you can actually go
simpler, and that's going to give you uh
a more interesting looking animation.
So, I'm going to hit the drop down, hits
on, hit on scene, world, scene, lights,
and we're going to go get a light area.
Hit up. Let's see. We need to go see the
gizmos. I'm going to go here to actually
we'll just keep it flat.
And then we'll bring it up.
I always put my lights way too close.
And I'm going hit R twice. And then
scale the thing up pretty aggressively.
And then give your power of like 3,000.
So that's starting to look good. Um,
let's bring that spread in a little bit.
And then you can go maybe uh 10,000.
All right, that looks that looks pretty
good. And then you can also bring your
world brightness up a little bit if you
want to even out those shadows or make
the shadows really aggressive and make
them super dark. Whatever you want to
do. And then here in the particle
system, I'm going to go open up that
window again that I sadly deleted. And
I'm going to bring up my density again.
So right now it's at 600. We're going to
do 1200
to make it fully nice and dense. And
then let's go ahead and render this out
and see how this would look as a final
image. All right. So, this is a final
look at what it would look like
rendered. One thing I think is the
shadows are too long for what I want it
to be. So, I'm going to just go ahead
and that tells me I just want to bring
up the height
of my light. So, I'm just going to go
ahead and say go up a little bit and
then point down. I still want a little
bit of that like what I'm getting. So,
that looks super nice. Now, what we need
to do is just animate our particles uh
in a loop so that this looks really
cool. So, that would be the W of this
noise texture. Right now, it's way too
dense to see that in real time. So, I'm
going to do maybe a density of 50 for
now so we can look at these particles
move in real time. So, let's go ahead.
I'm going to highlight this and hit G
and move them down. And let's go ahead
and get ourselves some space. So,
I'm going to hit I'm going to hit shift
and rightclick just to keep these two
connections uh the same. I'm going to go
ahead here on the W, make it zero. We're
going to duplicate this noise texture.
We're going to get a mix color node and
plug these two here. So, now what we're
going to do is loop the W. So, now the
scale is really small. So, the W values
are going to need to be pretty high for
this to to move. I mean, relatively
fast. So, what I'll do is we'll go make
sure in your preferences in the
animation tab, your default
interpolation is linear. And then what
I'll do is here in the W, I'm going to
hit I. Here in the factor, bring it to
the left, hit I. I'm going to go to the
end, bring that factor over, hit I, and
then we're going to do a uh a scale of
four. And then right here, now that
we're at the very end, hit I. Go to the
end and type in -4 because we did
positive four on the other one. And we
should see, let's see, is this real
time? That's 14 frames a second. So, we
need to bring this density to like 10.
There we go. So, this is real time. So,
this is as fast as your particles are
going to be moving um once you're done
rendering it. I think this is a really
nice speed. Now, for my final, I'm going
to go ahead and save my file. And then
for my final, I want my density to be
1,200. So, we have a lot of particles.
The lighting will hit them. The thing
about having lots of uh thing about
particle systems is if you have small
particles, you need a large volume of
them in order for the lighting to
actually uh hit it and look good and it
feel nice. Uh much like making this
whole particle system as a collective be
one single solid object. So that is uh
sometimes why maybe you feel like your
particle systems don't look good. It's
because you don't have enough particles.
But now that we're finished, this is a
final. I can actually say, okay, make it
the full density. We can go ahead and
render this out. So, as for your render
settings, I'm going to go 1920 x 1080.
I'm going to do a uh p I'm going to tell
it to do a PNG sequence, and then I'll
sequence that together. If you don't
want to do a PNG sequence and you just
want Blender to give you MP4 out the
box, which I don't encourage, but you
totally can. Um, we can go here to a
FFmpeg video, pick your file, encoding
to MP4
or QuickTime if you're on Mac, and then
medium quality to perceptually lossless.
render render animation and when you're
done you'll have something really cool
like mine. So there you go. Hope you
guys enjoyed it. Again, if you want to
learn tons of more really cool things
about particle systems and geometry
nodes, I have a whole series on my
Patreon. You can check that out in the
description. But with that, I hope you
learned something cool. Hope you can
apply this to other things. and I'll see
you in the next one.