How's it going? In this tutorial, I'm
going to show you how to create this
animation right here. There's actually
going to be two animations in this
tutorial that you'll be able to pick
from, or you can do both. Here's the
steps that we're going to go through to
create this animation. First, we need to
simulate an array of curves. Then, we're
going to go ahead and displace those
curves. Each curve needs its own W value
to give it a little bit more of a
realistic stringy look. Then we can use
a little bit of math to isolate the
displacement to the center. Or we can
use a different set of nodes to animate
the string coming in and out. After
that, we just need to add some color,
add some lighting, and we'll be done.
This is a geometry node tutorial. And if
you are new to geometry nodes, don't
worry. We're going to be going step by
step, and I'll be explaining everything.
This tutorial is actually a free lesson
from a series of tutorials I just did on
Patreon talking about using simulation
zones as a way to create arrays which
helped go around a few kind of stumbling
blocks in geometry nodes to make some
really really interesting animations.
You can find the collection on my
Patreon called the simulation arrays and
it just dives into that idea. You can
check out my Patreon linked in the
description and let's dive into this
tutorial. So, first we're going to go
ahead and throw a piece of geometry into
our scene. And I'm going to go and cut
my window in half up here. We're going
to switch it over to the geometry nodes
editor. I'm going to hit N to move that.
We're going to get a new window and
we're going to go ahead and delete this
input and we're going to go ahead and
get a quadratic bezier. So, shift a
search quadratic bezier. We're going to
plug it right into here. First, what
we're going to do is notice this
quadratic bezier is just curved right
now. I'm going to go ahead and click and
drag. Bring it down to zero. And on the
y-axis, we're going to give it a value
of four. That's going to stretch that
curve that direction. And we're going to
give it a resolution of 400. Now, we're
going to go ahead get a
transform geometry node. And I just want
to bring this curve here to the center
of the scene. Not necessary, but it's
just something that I like uh to have
everything centered out. And then now
we're going to go ahead and add the
simulation zone. Now, if this is your
first time using simulation zones, this
is actually a perfect gateway into it.
So just search simulation
and we're going to go ahead and plug
these here. So what we want to do
is simulate a movement. And what I want
to do is get a transform geometry. And I
want to simulate it going this
direction. And what a simulation is
going to do is repeat an action every
single frame. And so what I want to do
is to go 01, duplicate another one at
that distance every frame. And so what
we need to do is get a join geometry
node. And then we we're just going to go
ahead from outside of the simulation
zone do that. Now make sure you're not
doing this. That's going to in be insane
for your computer. We want to go outside
of it. Otherwise, it's going to be
duplicating geometry way too much. So,
now that we have this, if I press play,
we're now getting an array. Now, the way
that I used to do this is to get a a
line and then instance objects on the
points of that line. The problem is when
I want to go ahead and displace the
curves that are instance on that line,
it displaces the line, not the curves on
the line. Hope that makes sense. This
goes around it and offers some really,
really cool things that I dived into on
Patreon. So, a lot of really cool things
to explore just with the simple idea
with simulations. Now, with me, you can
see I have 46 frames. That means I have
46 objects. I want to get about 38.
And then we can
we can bake this in just like that. And
it's going to tell you we have baked
frame 38. In this case, that means we
have 38 instances. Now, what I want to
do is get another transform geometry and
just bring this guy to the center as
well. Again, not necessary. It's really
just for me. Um, now let's go ahead and
displace this. So, we're going to get a
set position node and we're going to get
a noise texture. So, what I want is to
displace it only on the X. So, we need
to get a combine
XYZ node which will allow us to now have
access to one single axis. Plug factor
into Z. And then I'm going to use the
normalize. Notice how it kind of went
above. Normalize will keep it centered.
But now this is far far too strong. So
we can use a math node to edit the
strength of this effect with the
multiply function. Multiply is going to
play with the strength of a particular
action. So now we can bring the detail
down to zero. We can bring that scale
up. Actually, maybe bring the detail a
little bit up. And then switch this over
to 4D. And we can look at that movement.
There is one thing that I don't
particularly like with this idea. Notice
how all of the strings are kind of all
the strings are being affected by the
same exact noise texture, specifically
the same value of the W. All these
things are the same, right? And so the
value of the W is like a seed value, but
all of them are being animated. So they
kind of look connected like a like this
wave. All of them have this wave this
way and this way and it's all you know
they all look in relation to each other
way in in this wave together that
doesn't give this really stringy organic
look that I personally want for this
which means I want each one of these
strings to have its own value of the W.
So say like this string is on this value
2.48 48 and another string is going to
have this value which will put them at
random points which is what I want. Now
how do you do that? I'm going to go
ahead and give myself a little bit more
space here and we're going to get an
attribute. So we're going to get a store
named attribute node. We're going to get
a random value and we want to use a
random value for the W giving each one
of these strings its own random W value.
How do you do that? So here in the store
named attribute, I want it to recognize
the splines. We're just going to give it
a name of R just for random. And you can
plug this right here. So now that we
have an attribute that is assigning a a
unique value to each one of these
strings cuz it recognizes each one of
those curves through telling it to
recognize curves and assign a random
value to each one of those curves.
That's what this does. So now we can get
a attribute node, a named attribute
call. Looks like it's a capital R. I
don't know why I did a capital. And then
watch what happens if I go ahead and
plug this attribute into the W. Instead
of now just one value, we're getting
multiple values in the W. And this is
awesome. Two things. We can't adjust the
strength of this effect. And we also no
longer have an ability to animate the W.
But we could fix that with a math node
right here. So if you play with add, if
you just want to animate, the add
function right here is exactly
the W slider. See that? It does the same
exact thing, but in case we now have
access to it. So now it's randomly uh
animating the W of all these random
values. But what we can do is actually
get a multiply add node. And if you
bring the multiply to zero, it's like,
okay, we're no longer random randomizing
it. And so you can just kind of bring in
a little bit of randomization. So it
still looks like they're all kind of a
part of this big wave, but they still
have a little bit of individuality to
them. Or you can kind of go crazy with
it and have them all just look like
they're doing their own thing. I do kind
of like a mix of this and that, giving
it just a little bit of this organic
stringy motion, but they're all kind of
wave and a wave together in this kind of
interesting way. We're going to go ahead
and isolate this uh displacement. But
first, I kind of want to look at some
geometry to make it look better. So,
we're going to go ahead and get a curve
to mesh
and we're going to get a curve circle
for the geometry. So, I'm going to give
it a radius of 0.4 and plug curve into
profile. Now, we have our strings and we
can go back and kind of look at how that
looks. It looks really cool and I love
it. So, what I want to do is just have
the displacement centered right here to
the middle. So, we're going to go ahead
and mix two things. We're going to mix a
flat
value and this whole situation here. So,
what I'm going to do is going to mix
vector. Now, we could use vector if we
want. Uh, these are floats, so we're
just going to use mix float just to keep
it all uh technically correct, but the
the vector would work, too.
Now, we're going to mix this state with
this state, and we're going to do that
with the factor. So, what we can do, I'm
just bring this down here.
We're going to get a position node, and
we're going to get a math node. I'm
going to plug position into value and
value into factor. And it's going to do
this. If I play with the value,
you can notice
it's animating in. It's animating this
dis this displacement in. Now, one thing
I want to do is make sure any effect I
do is actually moving this direction.
So, what we're going to do is get a
separate XYZ
and
confine it to the Y. Because if I play
with the value now, you can see it's
going the other direction from left to
right. So, I wanted to make sure because
once we add our pingpong function, it is
going to
need to be told which way to go. So, now
we have this really cool function which
you can also animate automatically. This
is really cool and fun. So, we have this
and now we're going to go ahead and add
in a pingpong function to make sure that
we can go from displacement flat
essentially go flat displacement flat.
And that is a ping-pong function if
you're going one back to another. And so
we're going to go ahead and get another
math node and we're going to get D, if
we can find it, ping pong. So if I bring
that value up, you'll notice,
bring that value into the negative, it's
going to kind of isolate this. And so we
can just bring this guy to the center
with our value. But notice what this
ping pong is doing. So it is doing a lot
of like multiple ping pongs, which just
makes it look regular. um bring that to
a larger negative value. And now what
it's taking is flat going to
displacement and then going back to
flat. That's what this function is doing
in a really sort of layman's turn term
way. So what we can do now is we can get
another math node
to edit the size
of this ping pong function. So this add
function plays with the position of
where it's happening and this plays with
the size which opens up an ability to
actually animate it coming in. So I want
to isolate it to somewhere around there.
And then you can play with your multiply
down here to say how strong you want
that effect. And then you can animate it
right here. And it's really really
controllable and fun. So that's the
first animation. You can just go ahead
do that if you want. Now, I'm going to
bring this all the way to the to the I'm
going to bring this one all the way out
so we can see all the displacement. What
we can also do is trim it. So, what I
can do is I'm going to just bring these
guys over here and get a trim curves
node. And if you play with the end,
notice
you can animate these guys actually
coming in. Now, notice these are hollow.
If you go here to the uh curve to mesh,
it'll fill that up. But it's pretty
cool. We can now animate this in. But
what's not cool, at least with the style
that I want, is that just it's just like
you took scissors and cut it. I want to
randomize
um where they're at. And you could do
that with a
random value. Just plug a random value
into the end function. And let's just
give them both a value of zero and
animate it in. So, see that? You just
click and drag if you want them both to
go together. And then I'll just pull one
back.
And now you have a little bit more of a
natural look. And then if you click and
drag them both, they'll just travel
together. And now we have a really,
really cool thing. So there you have
that. I'm going to give them a value of
one. And I'm going to go back to uh this
effect. I'm going to go ahead and add
our lighting. and all that stuff uh with
this this look. This is my favorite look
of the two, but both animations I can
see, you know, people wanting and I
wanted to show you guys you could do uh
multiple things here. So, now we have
this really cool effect. So, I think I'm
ready to go ahead and add a camera, add
some lighting, have a little bit of of
fun with it.
Just making some adjustments personally.
Okay, let's go ahead and add a material
to this. So, I'm going to go here to the
end, get a
set material node. And before we switch
over to the shading, I do Let's go ahead
and create a material. Before we switch
over to the shading, I want to remind
you we have an attribute over here that
creates a random value. So, just
remember that because we are going to
use that in just a second um in the
shading. So, there's nothing I want to
do in this window right now. So, I'm
just going to go ahead and switch it
over to the shader editor. And now we
have that material material 001. You can
see we're using it by seeing that up
there. So first let's get that attribute
node and I'm going to switch this over
to the material preview.
If I plug So if I type in the letter R,
which is going to call that attribute
that we called to create the randomness,
and we plug factor right into base
color, we can see it's actually creating
a little bit of randomness, random
color, which is great. That's what I
want. Um, in this particular style,
we're just making it look cool with some
random color.
So, I'm going to go ahead and get my
color ramp. We're going to get two
colors. We're going to get kind of a a
lightish gray. And then we're also going
to go ahead and get
something like that. And then we're just
going to bring these two in.
So, now we have pretty cool style. What
I want to do is I'm going to go here to
cycles. Give myself some lights for now.
And here in the subsurface, I'm going to
bring that weight up. Now, you can
notice it kind of looks like skin,
especially in the parts where there's
shadow. That's just cuz these auto these
default settings are uh set up for skin.
If you just give them all a value of
one, it'll just make them look normal
quote unquote normal. It just doesn't
add that skin kind of look. And then if
you bring that scale up,
it this scale is what says how much
light we're letting into this. So this
looks really nice. I'm going to go ahead
and park with this and bring this window
over. We're now going to deal with
lighting. So I'm going to go and select
my camera angle.
Probably something like this. I'm going
hit control alt0. Snap it to view. And
I'm going to give myself a focal length
focal length of like 120. I want this to
look really flat
in terms of the the the lens
essentially. And so maybe something like
that.
Cool. Okay. So, we're going to go ahead
and add some lighting. So, I'm going to
bring this down and go just the scene
world scene lights. So, we're going to
get a light hitting it directly that
way. So, let's go ahead and get an area
light. I'm going to switch it over to a
disc.
Bring it over.
I'm going hit R twice
and then bring that give it a power of
like I don't know 80. And then we can
bring that spread down
to something around
these lines. And then maybe bring that
power back down a little bit. And then
bring that scale up some, too. Okay. So,
we kind of have some soft lighting.
Maybe bring that power up. What I want
to do, I'm going just turn on my
denoising. And I want to get a
background, a nice soft background. And
so, we're going to kind of do it maybe
not in a totally traditional way. So,
I'm going to take this. I'm going to do
RX.
I'm going hit R Y90.
And then I want to bring this back far
enough to where it can't it can't be
affected by this light anymore. I want
to be able to control it uh independent.
And then I'm going to bring it down to a
point where we can see it in the camera.
And then we're going to get a point
light.
I hit G
and just get this point light to be
affecting
our background. So, I'm gonna get a
render region.
And so, now we can play with this point
light
to be a nice highlight in the
background. And if you want, which I'm
going to do, I'm going to go over here.
I'm going to go back to the shading and
I'm going to hover over here and copy
that color. And then in the point light,
I'm going to go ahead and paste that
color. And then just bring the
saturation down.
That's just a good look.
And there we have it. If you want to
bring that world brightness down to
black, you can. That's going to give it
more of a dramatic look, which again
could be something you want. Then of
course, if you don't like the sort of
how dramatic these dark shadows are
here, you can add another light, another
area light
down here. just to point at the bottom.
And then you can control that.
So something like this. There we go. Now
you have a lot of control. So I'm going
to go ahead and render this frame just
to see how it looks as a final. So this
is our final look. You can play with the
lighting. I mean everything. You can
play with everything to get it to be
exactly how you want it to be. So, I
want to go back to geometry nodes just
to show you where you can animate it and
just allow you to kind of make that
decision for yourself. So, we can go
back to the geometry nodes editor and
look at all of our animation
possibilities.
If we go here to this big mix of math,
we have this string of guys up here. You
can play with this first value node to
kind of bring this effect in like that.
Now, if you do that, if you animate from
here to here, I would recommend do it
while simultaneously
animating this W value on the ad end.
So, it gives it way more life. So, you
can do that. You also have this add node
animating this growth
just like that. And again, if you're
going to do that, I would say have this
W value moving while this guy comes in
and out. And then of course
you have this trim curve node.
You can go ahead and give it a little
bit of randomness.
And then I would say bring the strength
down a little bit for this effect. And
then you can play with that trim curves
to animate in just like that. And this
is the one that I would say maybe don't
animate the W value. I do like this,
you know, I like how that looks. But
again, it is all completely up to what
you want to do, how you want to animate
it, and I'll leave that completely up to
you. So, that is how you create this
string effect. It's really, really
powerful. Tons of different ways you can
do this, controlling the curves, adding
textures, adding materials, different
context to make this really, really
useful in your own animations. But with
that being said, thank you guys for
watching. Again, if you want to check
out the full collection of tutorials on
my Patreon, that is linked in the
description, and you can get a discount
if you subscribe annually. And I'll see
you guys in the next