how's it going guys so in today's
tutorial we're going to be learning how
to make this really cool kind of
parasite effect it's using 100 geometry
notes and it's really fun before we get
into that all of my products are 25 off
right now including real-time materials
if you use the code ducky summer at
checkout you will get 25 off on my
shading course my animation course and
of course real-time materials with that
being said let's get into the tutorial
all right so one thing that's very
important for you to be able to follow
along with this tutorial is you need to
go ahead and Google blender daily builds
or builder.blender.org and right here
you're going to want to get the 3.3 beta
as of recording this video right now
blender 3.3 is in beta and if you're
watching this several months
um from today's date it might be in a
stable build so you won't need to go to
this you'll already be at 3.3 or 3.4 3.5
whatever but as of today you'll need to
get this download that zip file unzip
the file and open up the blender execute
file uh with that being said once you
open it up just go ahead and clear out
your scene and then I'm going to be
using Cycles to render this out so my
Max bounces here in the light pads
everything is set to one and reflective
and refractive are completely off and
then if you want to follow along in
Eevee which you totally can
um you go ahead and turn on Bloom
ambient occlusion screen space
Reflections and your motion blur but I'm
not sure blur really works in this
animation with that being said let's go
back to Cycles or stay in that engine I
am going going to go ahead and render at
800 samples
all right so let's go ahead and get in a
plan so shift a add in a plane that's
the only real amount of geometry we're
going to be goofing with this is going
to be totally geometry nodes so click on
your geometry nodes Tab and I'm going to
go ahead and turn off this window I
never use it
um but let's go ahead and click new
and then delete this input
we don't really need that plane we're
going to go ahead and go ahead and shift
a search
volume
and then we're going to go here and get
the volume Cube and that's going to go
ahead and get us this some fog looks
like you have a cube with a principled
volume on it let's go ahead and type in
volume again and get volume to mesh now
we have kind of a beveled Cube
so if you've never used the volume Cube
before it's a fun little tool you can
make this really cool volume Cube and
it's there's not a lot to it to be
honest and I have made a video on it in
the past but really the most important
thing to know in this tutorial for the
volume cube is right over here is your
resolution so if you click and drag it
will up your resolution so now you just
have massive amount of faces so if we go
to the wireframe view you can see that
if I click and drag and bring it back
this is your subdivision for the cube so
that's really important to note I'm
going to keep mine at 50 for now but
we're going to render it at 100. or
really whenever your computer can handle
sometimes you can't sometimes you can
handle more
now with that being said
we want to turn this into a circle and
there's no there's not a volume Circle
there's not a volume Taurus there's just
a volume Cube so what we need to do is
get a gradient node
gradient texture and go to spherical and
that is just going to go ahead and turn
it into a circle which is pretty neat
very simple let's go ahead and smooth it
out with a set shade smooth node that's
all we're going to need to do that but
now we need to take a noise texture and
kind of destroy this but there's no real
obvious way to do it because we're
already using the input to destroy it
typically you just put a noise texture
in it and destroy the cube
so this is what we have to do let's go
ahead and get a mix RGB and we'll plug
the gradient texture into the factor and
then bring color one all the way to
Black and that's going to give us our
Circle back and we use this output right
here to put textures into it
the texture we're going to use is a
noise texture but you can use any
texture you want it's a really really
fun to play with you can even pause the
tutorial Now find a texture that you
like and goof around with it our scale
we're going to do 1.7 on the scale make
sure it's 4D and that's so that we can
animate it and then we need to go ahead
and get a color ramp
color ramp goes here and that's going to
allow us to eat into this and so when we
play with that W now we have the look
that we're going for this used to be a
lot more difficult you'd have to use
like vertex groups and weirdness
now with geometry notes it's just super
easy to do so this is done we can Loop
it but we'll go ahead and loop the
animation later I want to go ahead and
build kind of a cage around it now we're
getting the point we can just kind of
make this really cool looking
um so we're gonna go ahead and get a
join geometry node
this is almost like a mixed Shader if
you're familiar with nodes node-based
shading
the geometry nodes isn't going to be too
crazy to understand especially if you're
pretty good at node-based shading this
is essentially a mix Shader what we need
to do is get an icosphere
put that over here and plug that
straight into the joint geometry you
just put it anywhere the uh the order
doesn't matter if it's above or below
them as far as I'm aware now let's go
ahead and get in a mesh to curve that's
going to turn this into kind of a
wireframe and then I'm going to go ahead
and bring my radius down a little bit I
like the kind of parasite goo whatever
to kind of intersect
um the wireframe so it's kind of caged
in but it's still trying to come out
gives it a little bit of a story and now
let's go ahead and get to curve to mesh
curve to mesh put that there and to kind
of initiate that we need to get a curved
Circle
so just type in circle and then the
radius is going to dictate
how big that bar is going to be so add
the curve and then bring that radius
down
and now we have
a bit of a cage that this is going to be
encapsulated in but I also want to now
add some spheres around each point the
point is kind of the corners so using
that word point we need to get an
instance on point
so we'll do a instance on points
and we will plug the icosphere into the
points selection so it says use these
points and we're going to plug an object
in the instance as what object we are
going to instance so let's plug this
into the genome geometry and let's get
another icosphere
all right here icosphere and plug that
icosphere into the instance
and then we're going to bring that
radius down so now you can see it's on
each point which is really really cool
and then bring those subdivisions up a
little bit on that icosphere you know
really whatever you want
um and we have it now you can see those
faces let's go ahead and get that set
shade smooth node I'm gonna hit shift d
put it there
perfectly smooth all right now we have
this guy personally
I think we should bring this maybe 0.02
that looks about right that looks really
good maybe
one five right in between those two all
right cool perfect perfect perfect
it looks awesome It looks interesting
and we now have something really awesome
now that we have this whole scene set up
let's go ahead and loop the animation of
this so let's go ahead hover over here
you'll see a plus icon just drag that up
and then we're gonna go to a timeline
so go to your edit preferences here in
the animation tab right here make sure
your default interpolation is set to
linear that's really important and I'm
going to give myself 120 frames that's
going to be about five seconds but this
is going to be a seamless Loop so it can
be infinite and it won't be obvious so
let's go ahead and take this noise
texture and make sure make sure your W
is set to zero and if you don't have W
right here you need to make sure that
your node is 4D
so let's go ahead and just hit shift d
duplicate that get a mix RGB plug that
there plug factor into color two make
sure you're using Factor not color on
both of these so let's go ahead and
animate so right hover over your
timeline hit the back arrow to go to
frame zero hover over here and hit I
and then go to the end and just slide
that over and then hit I again that's
going to give it a keyframe now if you
click on it you can't see your keyframes
that's normal I don't know why it does
that but sometimes you just can't see
your keyframes
go back to frame zero right here on this
w
hit I go to the very end and type in one
so that's going to make your W go to a
value of one it's going to animate a
little bit if you want your animation to
go quicker use two three four five you
know however strong you want it to be
now that we're at the very end go to
this one hover over the W make sure it's
at zero hit I go to the end back to
frame zero and since we use positive one
on this one
negative one at the very end
oops
delete keyframes there we go negative
one so now we can see it animates if we
go to the end it's a perfect Loop and
again I mentioned if you want to be
faster don't use a value of one using a
value of two and then if you go to the
very end make sure this one is negative
two so they relate
but with that being said we now have
this and if you want to know like what
would this look like for res
go here to this node
a hundred it looks really cool and very
goopy and strange but we now are done
modeling we're done with the modeling
section and animation section
we're pretty much done but I always like
to leave you guys with something you can
walk away with have something you can
post show whatever so let's build an
environment around a very simple one
so I'm gonna hit the tilde key which is
right above the Tab Key I'm going to
click front
shift a add a camera and I'm going to
hit Ctrl alt 0 that's going to snap that
camera to view and say it's like way out
here or way in here just hit G and
middle click and that'll slide it out
to where you want it to be there we go
look how cool that looks
so let's go ahead and build a scene
around this so I'm going to be using
Cycles you don't have to use Cycles you
can use EV just really depends on your
preference and your Hardware
so here in the world icon I'm going to
go ahead and bring it all the way down
to Black
and then I want to have a light that's
really big and behind this so you get a
really soft lighting and you also get
some silhouette so I'll go ahead and get
a point light and I'm going to hit G and
I'm going to move it
here so it's behind and it's up
so it really does not to be need to be
an exact science so we're going to go
now here to the Cycles view I'm going to
give my power at 10 000.
and that you might say oh that's way too
bright and that's because we're going to
bring this radius
really high up so now it's super soft
um now that we're here let's go ahead
and add the volume so go to the World
Properties volume right here in volume
go to principled volume
now it's going to take everything away
right here in your density 0.01
on the point light setting so click on
your point light go to the settings make
it whatever color you want I love a
slight blue now we're here let's go
ahead and add materials to this
in Geometry nodes it's a little bit
weirder to make to add materials you
can't just add them the typical
traditional way
so go here to this join geometry each of
these strings represents a piece of this
pie in a sense so this string is the goo
this string here would be the wireframe
and this string here would be those
spheres on each point so we need to add
a set material node
so set material and then shift d
plop them on each side now we need two
materials we need the goo that's a
glowing goo and the kind of basic
material so right over here click this
click new I'm going to call it
goo
I'll click another one and we're going
to call it base
the reason why we're titling them is
over here you have to be able to see
them so it's more important to tile them
I used to never need to dial them let me
title them with that being said let's go
ahead and click goo here
base
base now let's go here to the shading
Tab and work on texturing these guys
shading them whatever term you like to
use
so we on slot two which is the base keep
that in mind slot one is the goo slot
two is the base uh so base color bring
that to Black and bring your roughness
almost all the way down now we have this
beautiful shiny black material now let's
go here to slot number one which is goo
we're gonna do the same thing
really low roughness bring that specular
all the way up so you get really bright
Reflections you can even go up to like
two really bright Reflections you can
really force it uh with those values and
then here we need to go add some
emission so let's get a color ramp
and we want a smooth gradient so we're
going to go to B spline and we need a
layer weight
layer weight and use the facing
and then plug the color into the
emission
so now when we play with this blend it's
going to go back to the edge let's go
ahead and bring this color ramp in so
now we get this effect
the white go ahead and add whatever
color you want I'm gonna go with green
because it's very sci-fi and
you guys know I love the Sci-Fi Styles
I'm going to go ahead and just remove
this background it's just preference and
then bring that up that emission
strength and you're going to have
something crazy I'm gonna go to Cycles
and tweak this a little bit
something like this
bring that emission strength really high
we want to be able to Glow really nicely
there we go we have this looks awesome
looks clean looks nice and our light is
too bright it's because of our uh
specular so we can bring that specular
back to one bring your specular down it
really just depends on how you want
that to look let's bring that specular
back to two and bring our light down
might be too bright so let's go five
thousand
there we go that looks really nice and
it'll still be able to glow and we can
bring that radius higher which is
exactly what we should have been doing
originally
so we can capitalize on these
reflections
possibly bring that light back a little
bit not sure what good that's gonna do
but I'm going to hit G and move it back
this is just kind of messing around
preference here
maybe eight thousand
cool so now we have these Reflections
bring that
higher now we're just goofing around
what are we doing
cool
all right it's good enough and then if
we press play we get these nice
Reflections I would tweak it farther
I would edit it farther to make it look
cool but for the sake of the tutorial
this is how it looks maybe bring some
roughness in
oh yeah there we go now that looks even
better just a softer Edge which is
something we like all right now
um we're done we're pretty much done
with the tutorial
let me show you guys how to export this
and we will be done so click on the
printer icon go ahead and select your
resolution I love to just keep it at
default 1920. if you're a big fan of 4K
just type in 200 on that value and
that'll make it 4K
um frame frame rate's fine go ahead and
make a new file on your desktop or
wherever and click this plus icon and
I'm going to call this
and then double click it and accept
that's going to save all your pngs
um I would highly recommend doing a PNG
sequence and then just go ahead and
render
render animation and you'll be done now
if you just want blender to compile a
video for you you don't have to compile
the PNG sequences especially if you're
using Eevee it probably won't crash go
from PNG to ffmpeg video encoding go
here to MP4 and output quality
perceptually lossless render render
animation
and you'll be done uh but with that
being said that is how you create that
animation I hope you learned some stuff
again all of my products are 25 off for
the rest of the week if you want to
check that out Linked In the description
and I'll see you guys in the next
tutorial
[Music]