How's it going, guys? So, in this
tutorial, we are going to be creating
this animation right here. It's going to
be really fun and relatively quick to
make. First thing we're going to do is
make a circular array of curves. Then,
we're going to go ahead and displace the
curves and shape them to look a little
bit more like hills. Then, through a few
steps, we're going to use a wave texture
to create this really beautiful
animation. After that, we'll be
completely done. This animation is part
of a series of tutorials here on YouTube
that are inspired by topographic map art
and animations. I'll be posting four of
these tutorials backtoback here on
YouTube. So, if you want to learn more
of this stuff, you can go and check out
the other ones like this. They're all
really cool and there's a lot of fun
things to learn. On Patreon, I posted
what I'm calling the topographic
blueprint, which is an hour and 20
minutes of training of all the shading,
geometry nodes, and animation tricks
that are combined to make these four
animations and many others. Here on
YouTube, all those elements are combined
to make really cool animations. But on
Patreon, I'm showing you every
individual effect and tip and trick so
that you can combine them and make your
own original topographic map inspired
animations. So, if you want to check
that out, that is going to be linked in
the description and you can get a
discount if you subscribe annually. With
that being said, let's get into this
tutorial. All right. So, first, let's go
ahead and throw in a piece of geometry.
I'm going to head into to geometry nodes
and just get my windows the way I like
uh to have, which is just one next to
the other with the geo nodes workspace
here. I'm going to go ahead and click
new and then delete the input. And we
are going to go ahead and get in a we're
going to hit shift a search cir a curve
circle. Plug it here. We're going to
give it a resolution of 300.
And now um when I want to make arrays
and geometry nodes and I'm displacing
that array immediately after, I like to
use a simulation zone to make the array.
So we're just going to go go ahead and
search up simulation. And let's go ahead
and plug
those into there. And then we're going
to go ahead and get in a transform
geometry node and a join to get this uh
to create the array. So get a join
geometry and then from outside the
simulation just go ahead and bring that
back in. And we are going to scale this
by 1.005.
That is going to get you just barely
next to it. And if you press play, it is
going to start duplicating
your circles. So just press play and
then watch the duplication happen. And
I'm going to get 111 cuz that is what I
used in mine. Really, you can do as many
or as few as you want. So now that we
have, you can see we have 100. It
creates one new instance or one new
object per frame. So we're going to go
ahead get a bake node and bake that out.
So now we can go back to the beginning
of our timeline and nothing's going to
change. Now let's go ahead. I'm going to
create a good amount of space because
we're going to put some attributes right
here later. But for now, let's just go
ahead and get a
set
position node and let's create the
displacement. So, we're going to get a
combine XYZ so that we can just displace
on the Z-axis. Let's get a noise texture
and plug color right into Z. And it's
going to do that. Let's click on
normalize and let's get in a vector math
node.
And let's switch that to scale so that
we can adjust the strength of this
effect. I'm going to give it a scale of
2.3
to look really cool. Just like that.
Now, what I want is there to be some
flat portions of this animation. And
normally you can just go ahead get a
color amp and it essentially kind of
clamps it on the bottom and you get
these nice flat portions. However, uh
it's a really dramatic change from flat
to curve. So, I don't particularly like
that. And if you want to get a little
bit more advanced on edits like this,
get a
RGB curves node. And then what you can
do is I'm just going to throw some
points right here, right here. And then
here, I'm just going to bring this up
just like that. And that is going to
make that uh a little bit flat, but
still have a little bit of nuance. And
then we can just switch this over to
we can click on here and switch this
over to more of a a harsh straight line.
You can even do that on this one. And
you get these flat portions but still
have a little bit of wave to them.
And you can just flatten out all of
these until you get some really nice
looking flat portions of your scene. And
then you can take the scale and bring up
the other portions. And that is going to
give you that topographic map inspired
look where you have these hills, you
have these flat portions, but still with
a little bit of wave to them, which is
really important for the style. And then
I can go ahead maybe bring my scale out
a little bit more. I still want more
flat.
This is pretty cool. So we can bring
that scale up some. So now we're here.
We can go ahead and start adding
materials. So, I'm going to go ahead get
a set material node right over here.
We're going to click new and I'm just
going to call this
light. You can call it whatever you
want. And then grab it here. So, right
before the material, we're going to go
ahead and get a
curve to mesh node. And we need to get a
circle. We're going to get a curve
circle node to define um the width of
the tubes. So, we're going to plug that
there. I'm going to do a resolution of
three and a radius of 0.001
for now. And we will make that thinner
later, but I want it big enough so we
can see the materials as we're editing
them. So now we have geometry. So if I
go over here to the shader and I click
on the light, I'm going to switch this
over to an emission node and then I'm
going to switch over to the EV engine
and let's look at it. So we have this
going on here. What I'll do is I'm going
to make this a little smaller so we can
just look at it here. And then I'm going
to bring up a new window. So I'm going
to keep geometry nodes up here and I'm
going to put the shading here. And let's
go ahead and plug a wave texture and a
color ramp into the color here on the
emission. So do a wave texture. And we
won't need a mapping because we're going
to do an attribute instead. So just plug
color right into color ramp. And notice
our first problem. this right here.
Notice how the wave uh it's it's going
across and even if I switch this over to
uh bands, it's still not going to
respect the direction of the curves
themselves. So, the way you can fix that
is right before the set position is
right before the set position, we're
going to add two attributes. So, we're
going to get a store named attribute.
We're going to get two of them. So, the
first one is going to be a
spline parameter node. And what is he is
going to be able to do is to tell the
shading which direction the curves are
going essentially at least at least from
a visual standpoint. So we'll plug
factor into value and we'll just name
them S for um spline. And then we're I
want to add some randomness to the um
phase offset. So we're going to get a
random value node. I want to add a
random value per curve. So we're going
to go from points to splines and then
plug that into the value. I'm just going
to call this R for random. So that's all
we're going to need to play with here.
So I can just go ahead and delete this
and we can get two attribute nodes. One
with the name R, one with the name S. So
the one with the name S is the is the
spline. So we'll plug factor into vector
and immediately it is going to respect
the direction of the curves, which is
really really nice. And then just to
make it look cooler, I'm going to go
from sign to saw. And it is going to
give the back end of it this really
faded uh faded edge and the front this
hard edge. So that when I bring in my
color ramp, uh you can have some fun.
And then I'm going to just go bring my
world brightness down to black. So this
is a little bit more of an obvious edit.
You can see that's how it looks now. It
looks pretty cool. Now what I want to do
is you notice how all of the waves are
in line with each other. I want to
randomize the position or how you know
where this is rotating per curve. And so
we created a random value per curve
attribute right here. So if I plug
factor into phase offset, see how it's
doing that? It's moving that. It's
giving it a unique value for each curve.
But it's not dramatic enough. I mean,
that might be cool. That's definitely a
cool look. I want it to be a little bit
more dramatic. So, I'm going to go ahead
and get a math node and switch it to
multiply add. I want to do a multiply so
I can multiply this effect to make it
look more like that and then add so we
can still animate all of them moving um
in a circle. So, one thing you can do to
edit this uh this look a little bit is
see how you can do that bring it all the
way down to this little point and then
you can use the add and animate these
guys around. What you can do is go ahead
and make this white as well. And then
get a new node and make him black. And
so now what we can do is bring him in
like this. Now what we can do is make
him a darker color and then bring it in
and make it much darker. Something like
this. So that the tips of each one of
these lines is brighter. And then it
goes from black from gray and then into
black like that. So it looks really
really cool. So you can do something
like this and get this really cool
effect. And then you can bring up your
strength
and then bring that down a little bit
more so that we can have a more obvious
effect. And then I'm going to go here to
the compositing window up here. Click
use nodes. Get a glare node and switch
it over to a fog glow. And then we can
go back to the geometry notes window
right up here. We can switch it to
always. And now we can see, okay, our
glow is working. And then when we uh use
the addend, we can see, okay, we can
move these guys around. Now, if you want
to change the color, you can get a mix
color node. Put this on the factor.
Bring this. Bring the top one down to
black and the bottom one. Choose any
color you want. So, I'm going to go with
something
something cool like this. Cool. So, now
we have this. Now, before we animate and
finish this off, one thing I want to
notice is all of these are animating at
the same speed at the same time using
this addend uh slider here. But what I
want is I want some of these uh curves I
want some of them to be faster and some
of them to be slower than others. And I
still want to animate this in a loop,
but I don't like that they're all going
the same. To me, it doesn't make it look
alive enough, similar to the way it
looks alive in my animation. So, here's
what we can do. I can get two materials.
One where the animation is going a
certain speed, and the other material
where it's going faster than the other
one. And I need to be able to assign
that to random ones. So, here's what we
can do. I can go back to the geometry
nodes editor
right here. And then right after the set
position right here, we're going to go
ahead and separate all of the curves so
I can assign two different materials.
One here and another one. So let's go
ahead and get a separate geometry node.
And we're going to say separate splines.
I'm going to get a
random value node and switch it to
boolean. That's going to make a slider.
So what's going to happen is if I plug
this into the selection, you'll notice
some of these start to delete. We're
deleting them. So I'm going to do 0.5.
So that means exactly we're deleting
half of them uh randomly. What this
means is now we have access to the ones
that we deleted through this inverted
output. So what I can do is I can take
these nodes here, hit control shift D or
just um duplicate them and connect the
inverted to the curve up here.
And then we're going to get a join
geometry.
And then watch, we're going to bring
them right back. So now
the ones that we separated are are um
you seen here, here, and here. And you
can notice, say I can bring up the
radius of some of them. See that? So now
the radius of some of them I can change
and other ones I don't. So they're
they're separated, which also means we
can make a separate material for each
one. So, right over here where it says
light, I'm going to hit the plus icon.
Hit this drop down. Click light. And
then I'm here. This number four, I'm
just going to click that. It's going to
make a duplicate of the material we
made. And I'm just going to call this
light
two. And grab light two here. So now
it's a literal duplicate of the material
that we just created. So when we go back
to
the shader editor, you can see slot one.
So light two. Watch what happens when we
play with the addendent. Some of them
aren't moving.
So, that's pretty cool. So, we can
animate them at different speeds when
we're ready to animate. What I want to
do is on some of these just make them
brighter than others just to give it a
little bit more of that randomness
uh look. I mean, you can even change the
color of some of them, too, if you want
to have some fun and uh make it look
awesome. You could do anything you want.
Have a lot of fun. And uh I'm just going
to make some of them darker. And then
I'm going to switch over to slot one,
the light, and make some of them
brighter.
so we can add more randomness to how
this looks. So, let's just go ahead and
animate them. So, I'm going to give
myself 400 frames. I'm going to go back
to frame zero and we're going to animate
this in a loop. So, I'm going to go back
here to the addend and go to zero.
Because we want this to be a loop, we're
going to use pi. So, I'm going to hit I
on the addend, go to the end, and I'm
going to type in -10*
or asterisk pi. We're doing negative 10
because um if you do a positive 10,
it'll look like it's going backwards. So
that's the only reason why we're doing
that. So now we have one animating at a
nice like slow pace. We're going to go
to slot two, which is light two. I'm
going to go back to frame zero on the
addend. Make sure it's at zero. I'm
going hit I. I'm going to do
I'm going to do -4
asterisk pi.
And now some of them are traveling
faster than others, which is going to
give it this more alive uh look. So now
we have this. We're done with the
animation. Let's just go ahead and
create a grid floor for the bottom.
So I'm going to go and just get my
camera. So I'm hit shift A camera. And
then I'm going to hit G and middle
click. I'm going to go up
and then then I'm going to hit RX.
Looks like I need to go up a little bit
more. RX.
And then I'll just go ahead and zoom in
so that we can have a nice camera angle
on this. Now, I want the floor to have a
nice grid cuz I just don't like like a
plain black background. I think it looks
kind of lame depending. It's not always
lame. So, I'm going to go ahead and get
a mesh plane. And I'm going to scale it
up
so it fits the screen. And then we're
going to go back to the geometry nodes
editor because we have the shader editor
opening there. And I'm going to get a
new material. Hit period to bring it
here. Get an emission of like three.
We're going to get a color ramp.
And we're going to get in a voronoid
texture. And then we're going to plug
distance into the color ramp. Bring the
random to zero. And then I'm going to
bring in my color ramp like that. So
let's bring up the scale.
And then I'm going to go to chvby chev
on the pattern.
And then
just going to play with the color ramp.
So bring it in like that. Bring the
white far to the left. And then we'll
just bring it in like this. And then
make the white portion blue like the
floor. Bring it up a little bit. We can
even make this a little bit
the line a little bit smaller.
So now
when I render this, we have this nice
grid floor for the bottom. So we are
completely done and we are going to be
rendering this in Eevee. If you don't
want to use Eevee and actually want to
use cycles, you can have a little bit
more fun and actually get a little bit
of reflection on the ground. So you can
make the bottom metallic, no reflection,
and you can have a little bit of
reflection on the ground if you want.
Uh, I'm going to make it easy for my
none uh my non cycles users and just
keep it in Eevee. And then when you're
done, you can just go ahead pick your
resolution. I'm going to keep it at 1920
x 1080. I highly recommend PNG
sequences, but you don't have to. If you
want Blender to just spit out uh
straight MP4, you can go from PNG to
FFmpeg video encoding to MP4 or
QuickTime if you're on Mac. Medium
quality to perceptually lossless.
Render, render animation. And when
you're done, you'll have something
really cool like mine. So there you go.
I hope you guys enjoyed it. Again, if
you want to check out that hour 20
minute edit of all of the ways, all of
the different features and unique really
cool things to make more of these
topographic map inspired animations, you
can check that out on Patreon and get
all of these project files as well. With
that being said, I'll see you guys in
the next