How's it going, guys? So, in today's
tutorial, we're going to be creating
this logo animation. We're going to be
using Geometry Nodes, and it's really,
really simple to build. First, we're
going to take the logo and distribute
some points on it. Then, we're going to
take that and make it a little bit more
3D and some ZSpace. Then, we can
displace it using a noise texture. After
that, we're going to distribute some
spheres and some flat planes so that we
can get a little bit of glitter and
brightness and some color distribution
in this animation. After that, it's just
going to come down to lighting
animation, and we're going to be done.
So, it's really, really simple, but
super effective and a really, really
cool animation. If you'd like to get the
finished project file, that is available
right now on my Patreon, along with a
ton of other training on the Patreon.
Every month, I'm releasing exclusive
tutorials on the Patreon. Quite often,
full collections that are thematic,
motion, graphics, or logos or text or
specific processes, and maybe shading or
geometry nodes. But there's a lot of
really cool things on the Patreon that
you can check out and learn even more
from. if you want to check it out,
that's going to be linked in the
description and you can get a discount
if you subscribe annually. With that
being said, let's get into this
tutorial. All right, so to start out, go
ahead and grab your logo. If you don't
have a logo and you just want to follow
along with this, I would say just take
some text and pick a letter that you
like, rightclick, and convert it to a
mesh and you will be good to go to
follow out the rest of this tutorial.
Now, if you have a logo in vector
format, what you'll do is go to file,
import, and select SVG. I'm going to go
ahead and grab my logo in SVG format.
And then I'm going to go ahead and scale
it up because they import really small.
At least mine does. And then I'm going
to hit tab just to get that anchor point
right there in the middle of my logo.
I'm just using G to move it. And then
very important just cuz it'll kind of
throw off your whole system. Make sure
you hit control A and apply the scale.
That's going to make sure the points
distribute um properly so that this
thing doesn't look like it's tiny. All
right, with that being said, let's go
ahead and I'm going to open up a new
window. and we are going to switch over
this window up here to the geometry
nodes editor and I'm going to click new.
So, first thing we want to do is hit
shift A and get a distribute points on
faces node and then we can just bring
out that density. But specifically
instead of random, go ahead and use
poison disc. What that's going to do is
give you this distance minimum. I'm
going to bring my density to say I don't
know one 1,000. And then you see this
distance minimum that is going to
prevent them from intersecting. But I
really just want it to be the smallest
it can be. Maybe
point 01 because these objects are going
to be really really small. Just having
the slightest bit of control over their
collision will go a long way. So we'll
take this density and now what I want to
do is make it a little bit thicker this
direction because that's going to just
make it look better. So we'll get a set
position node. We're going to get
a combine XYZ node because I just want
to move it on the Z. So that's going to
allow us to have access to a Z socket
and we're going to get a random value
node and plug it right into the Z. And
that's going to go ahead and
essentially extrude it. So maybe if you
don't want it all the way there, you can
kind of keep it in the middle. But
that's just about as thick as I'd like
it to be. And so now I'm looking at my
logo here. So, what we can do now is set
up the noise texture that is going to
actually be able to allow us to make all
these particles fly out in this really,
really interesting way. So, what I'm
going to do is just duplicate this set
position
node, get a vector math node, and we're
going to get a noise texture as our
pretty much like our displacement. So,
make sure that you use the color because
if you use factor, it's only going to
kind of move them what would look like
two axes. It's combining the XYZ into
sort of this random diagonal. The color
socket gives you multiple colors, which
gives you X, Y, and Z movement. So,
we're going to click on normalize to
keep everything in the middle and plug
color into vector. And you're going to
get this. Now, right now, it's at. We
need to switch this over to multiply.
What multiply in this case is going to
serve as a strength value. So, if you
just click and drag, it's going to
adjust the
strength of the noise texture. And
that's what we're going to use to um
that's this one we this is going to be
one of our animated values. Now you'll
notice these points look huge. And if
you're not ready to start instancing
objects in here and adding geometry,
what we're going to do is get
a set point radius node. And then you
can sort of bring them down a little bit
to get a better idea of okay, this is
going to be how it's going to look at
the end. So maybe we'll bring up that uh
density max to maybe 5,000. And then you
can go go back and play with that noise
texture. So what I want to do is switch
this noise texture over to 4D because
this is also going to be another value
that we're going to animate. And I'm
going to bring my scale to one and my
detail to maybe
five. And you'll see we'll get a really
really cool movement. And then the more
you bring that scale up, the more
interesting or really just more
different it's going to look. If you
like sort of a recognizable pattern, you
can bring that keep that scale around
the one, two, or three. Or if you want
it to be very just all over the place,
you can bring it to a larger value and
then it kind of looks like a cluster of
bugs or whatever coming in. But I tend
to like it to look like kind of a
discernable pattern uh to some degree. I
really prefer that. All right. Now, what
I want to do is instance some objects.
So, what we need to do is get a separate
geometry node because I want some of the
objects to be spheres and other objects
to be this flat uh these flat circles.
So, make sure it stays at the default
point. And what we're going to do is get
a instance on points node and we're
going to get a icosphere here and we'll
plug mesh into instance. And then we'll
bring that radius down. Uh but there's
no actual separation happening right
now. It's just instancing icospheres on
all of the points. We need to get a
random value node that is set to boolean
so that when we throw it into the
selection, you can actually separate.
And so see how there's missing there's
missing uh you know, we're deleting
points in a sense. That's cuz we have an
inverted socket. So all the spots where
you're seeing objects going away, they
are now those those spots are being
occupied by the other the inverted. So,
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
duplicate this instance on points. Plug
inverted into that. And we'll get a join
geometry node and plug instances into
geometry. And then we're going to get a
mesh circle and plug mesh into instance.
And they're going to be huge. First off,
we need to switch this over to inggon.
And then bring that radius in. I'm going
to give them vertices of six and then
bring that in again. And so now we have
a random distribution of each. What I
want is more uh spheres than I have
essentially these these they're they're
going to look like glitter in the
render. So, we're just going to keep
them at that. Right here in the
icosphere, I'm going to give it a
subdivision of one just to keep
everything smooth. And we'll get
a set shade smooth node. And then I'm
going to
get another random value
node and plug it into the scale of our
uh spheres. Looks like it's randomizing.
Yep. Okay. So, we have the We'll bring
these down. Bring these up a little bit.
I do want randomness in the scale of our
spheres. So, something
like that. And then we'll get another
random value node. And we need to plug
it into the rotation of the uh flat
spheres. And then we'll just randomize
it like that. And that is going to help
when the light hits them, they will uh
reflect really nicely. And then I do
want them to be a little bit smaller. I
want them to be kind of a subtle
glitter. And then now that we're here, I
still think the spheres are too big, but
I'm going to go ahead and bring up the
density
to 20,000. And then I'm going to go back
to my random value that's controlling
the spheres. And just bring them
smaller. Bring a couple bigger. And then
I think that's good. That's good for
now. we can go ahead and um add color
into the scene. So, I'm going to go here
to the material preview and we're going
to get two materials here in geometry
nodes. We're going to get a set material
node and just duplicate it. So, this see
where it says mesh circle. See that
line? So, this bottom one here that is
going to represent the metal or the
metallic gold material that we're going
to make and the other one is going to be
that nice red. So, let's select this
one. Make it kind of a interesting red.
You can really obviously do any color
you want. I'm gonna bring my roughness
all the way up. And then I'm going to
select it there. And then here on this
material, we're going to make it
metallic, pretty rough. And then a gold
color. And then grab it there. And so
now we
have all of that. So now we can go into
the lighting of this scene. So I'm just
going to bring this
uh I'm going to bring this geometry
window over a little bit.
And I'm going to go ahead and get a
camera. So, shift A, get a camera. I'm
going hit G and middle click. And then
just position it. We're going to right
over here in the camera settings. Give
it 24 mm. G and middle click
again. Something like that. And this
right here, my immediate thought is,
okay, the density needs to be higher on
um the density needs to be higher on how
many objects are in this scene. So, what
I'm going to do is right here on the
distance minimum, maybe
0.00 5 ought to give us a good amount of
density. So, that looks really, really
nice. So, now we can go ahead. I'm going
to bring this window back and we can go
into lighting. So, I'm going to go here
to the cycles view. I am using cycles
for this. I'm going to be dnoising my
scene and I'm going to be using 300 on
the samples. So, here in the world,
we'll bring it down to black.
I'm going to go ahead and get in a area
light. Hit G and we're going to do a
single lighting setup. This is something
I do really really often and honestly is
useful in so many cases. So, we're going
to use a disc shape. Going to make it
nice and big. And then we're going to go
here to the cycles preview and maybe
bring my power of
like 2,00 here in the world. We'll go
here to the volume and add a principled
volume node. And then 01 is going to
give us a nice volume. And then back to
the camera settings, we can bring that
spread down till we have a little bit of
black here. And then I'm just going to
go ahead and get a render
region. So looks like 2,000 is too
bright. Let's go with like 500 for now.
So here we go. We have this scene and it
looks really nice right now. I'm going
to click on this and go to the red here.
And I'm just going to go ahead and hover
over it. Hit Ctrl + C. Go to the camera.
I'm going to hit Ctrl +V. And then I'm
just going to bring the saturation down
so that we get this
uniformity I think is the right word.
Uniformity in the color. So now that
we're here, what I want to do is at
certain points in the scene, see how
this piece of metal is really bright?
It's really bright. It's reflecting.
It's directly reflecting that light.
It's going to be very very bright, but
it's hard to communicate how bright that
is if we don't have any compositing. So,
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
render out one frame and add some glare
in the compositor. All right, so we have
a frame rendered out. I'm going to go
here to the compositing. I'm going to
click use nodes. I'm going to go ahead
and get a viewer node. And then I'm
going to hit shift and uh rightclick.
And there we're going to get a glare
node. Plug it there. And then we're
going to go here to
uh to bloom. And then we're just going
to go ahead and on the highlights I'm
going to bring that threshold up just a
little bit so that we can just kind of
highlight those those points there. And
then we can go back. I'm going to say
click maybe and then you can hit this
drop down and click always and you'll
get to see those points. So now I'm
going to go and animate this. So bring
we're going to bring our window
back and then in the in your preferences
right here where it says linear. So go
to the animation preferences. Go here.
Switch it over to
bezier. And we're going to animate this.
So go to your vector math node. I'm
going to go ahead and bring it out to
something like that. I'm going to hit I.
Go to frame
200. And then type in zero and hit I
again. So this is the animation we have
so far. We'll just view it one more
time. Now, there's another piece of this
animation that uh we can add some
movement into it to make it look a
little bit more alive and more organic.
And that is going to be this W value.
But it's really really sensitive. So,
make sure we just do a little bit. So,
I'm going to hit I'm going to go back to
my preferences and switch this back to
linear. I'm going to hit I on the W, go
to 200, and I'm just going to move it a
tad bit to like 03 maybe.
And that is just going to randomly move
these objects around. Even 03 is too
much. Maybe
01. No, that was needs to be 0.1, not
01. 0.1. There we go. There we go. So,
now they're just moving around at a more
reasonable
speed. Nice. All right. So now I just
want to
view the
compositing. See these little glare
moments. So now we have these little
really nice little highlight moments
here in the scene. That's just going to
make it look a little bit more
beautiful. And then maybe even see the
random value that's connected to the
separated geometry. Just bring that
back. Maybe a few more pieces of
glitter. There we go. That's going to be
awesome. Okay, we are done with this
animation. So, I'm just going to close
the geometry nodes window. We can double
check this animation looks
proper. That looks really good. So, for
your render settings, I'm going to keep
it at 250 frames. Actually, no,
maybe 230. Just so after it after it
animates, it has some time to sit. I'm
going to keep it at 300 samples. Right
here on the printer icon, I'm going to
keep it at a PNG sequence. And then just
pick your F folder where you want to
throw all those PGs. I'm going to do
1080p. If you just want Blender to
export a a video for you, you don't want
to deal with PNG sequences, you can go
ahead to FFmpeg video um encoding
to MP4. And then you'll hit render
render animation. And when you're done,
you'll have a really, really cool
animation. So, there you go. That's how
you create a really cool logo particle
animation. It's really simple. Again, if
you want to check out the official
project file for this, that is available
on my Patreon for tier 1, 2, and three
members. You can check out all the
really cool stuff on my Patreon right
now. There's some free stuff. You can
also join as a free member, and you get
a discount if you subscribe annually.
With that being said, I hope you enjoyed
this. I hope you learned something and I
will see you in the next