How's it going, guys? So, in this
tutorial, we're going to be making this
render right here. First thing we're
going to do is hop into geometry nodes
and model the larger objects. Then,
we're going to use the same procedure
and make the smaller objects. And for
the first time on this channel, I'm
going to show you guys how to create
booleans directly within geometry nodes
to clean up that whole system. This
animation was inspired by Tron. So,
we're going to be doing a little bit of
wireframing to get that Tron inspired
look. Then after that, we're going to
hop into the shader editor and work on
detailing the metallic material on all
of those objects. Then my favorite part,
we're going to make a procedural
material on the floor to create that
really, really cool pattern. Then we're
going to bring it all together and
render out a really cool looking sci-fi
image. This tutorial is part of a larger
group of tutorials that I just put on
Patreon that's going to show you all the
different ways you can combine patterns
and processes and shapes and modeling to
create really, really cool looking
sci-fi scenes. It's six tutorials and
again available right now. If you want
to hit the link in my description, you
can check it out and you can get a
discount if you subscribe annually. With
that being said, let's hop into this
tutorial. All right, first we're going
to get the modeling portion out of the
way. So, what I'm going to do is just
hit shift A. We're going to get a plane
and I'm going to bring over just a brand
new window and make that my geometry
nodes editor. We're going to click new
and as always, we're going to delete the
input and we're going to start out with
a
grid
right here. It's over here. Let's make
it 10 by 10. And let's go ahead and
distribute. We're going to hit shift a
search distribute points on faces just
like this. And we're right now we're
going to model the big shapes. So we're
going to get the density at point 2 for
now. And we'll see uh how we feel later.
And let's get a instance on points node.
And of course we need to instance some
cubes. So let's plug him right into
instance. And now we have uh a random
distribution. Now to make this really
cool sci-fi, we need to go ahead and get
in a random value set to vector. The
reason why I want to do vector is
because we want to randomize X, Y, and Z
of all of these cubes, not just a
minimum and a maximum. So that would
keep essentially them what would be the
term uniform. In this case, if we do
vector, it's actually going to randomize
all options X, Y, and Z, which is really
cool. And what we're looking for. So on
these, we're just going to give them a
scale of two. And then here, my exact
settings were 4.4
two.
And then make them really short.
Something like this. And then maybe
bring him down as well. We want them to
be pretty short. We can edit how tall
they are a bit later, but right now
we're just focusing on large objects
here, the big pieces of the scene. So
now we have this and then there is a
seed value if you want something else.
And actually I think I saw something I
like
h I don't know
maybe bring the density down.
Yeah, this is good. Okay, so I think we
can work with this really really well.
Now what I want to do is distribute our
smaller pieces throughout the scene as
well. Actually this this is good. So now
what I want to do is get the small
details distributed next. So what we're
going to do is get a join geometry.
Same grid. We're going to get a
distribute points on faces and we'll
just plug that right into here. Now we
have a bunch of new points that we can
put another instance on points.
We'll just use the same cube. No need in
getting a brand new one.
Let's bring that density down to
something like
two. And we'll get another random value.
Set that to vector. And we'll go right
here into the scale. So right now
I'm just going to give them both a value
of one and just scale them down till I
like their kind of general size. And
then
we can make them small.
Stretch them out.
Something like that. Okay. So, these are
my exact settings for these small ones.
This is my exact settings for the large
ones. If we look at the wireframe now,
you'll notice everything is
intersecting. You can see there's a lot
of objects within the big objects. And
when it comes to wireframing them, it
will definitely highlight the fact that
objects are going inside of other
objects. That might not be preferable to
you. It's definitely not pref It's
definitely not preferable to me. So,
what we need to do is get a mesh boolean
right here. And I'm going to switch it
to union. Let me go back to wireframe.
And we can watch what happens,
especially in these bigger chunks. If we
just put it right here and there we go.
We now have mesh booleans going
everywhere in the scene. and it looks
really really cool. So then what's going
to happen is when we go to the
wireframe, the wireframe is actually
going to highlight that these objects
stop here rather than you can see
wireframes going inside of the object.
And it's really just not very
good-looking. If you want to be able to
view this better, you can hit this drop
down right here and do a cavity shadow
and outline. And that's going to make uh
looking at this a little bit e a little
bit easier. Next thing we could do is
add wireframes to this whole system on
this distribute points where it says
4.29.
I'm going to get a value node and just
paste that in there so I can remember
it. I'm just going to bring this down to
like 0.5 just to lighten up my scene
because it is really really heavy. And I
want to add some wireframe. I want to
add materials. And every movement we
make is going to kind of bog down. So
I'm just going to keep this as a
reminder. Set this lower and we can move
on. So, what I want to do after the mesh
boolean is get a
mesh to curve
and a
curve to mesh node and get a curve
circle
there. We're going to give it a
resolution of six because we aren't
really going to see that many. It
doesn't need to be high poly. And then
I'm going to do 01.
Plug that into the profile. And we now
have a wireframe of everything. What I
want to get is a join geometry. And
right at the mesh boolean, just bring
everything back. We now have uh
wireframes on everything. And let's go
ahead and click on fill caps and bring
the radius to like 06, maybe 0.6, just a
smaller wireframe. And we're ready to
move on. Last thing I want to do here in
this grid, just plug that into our join
geometry. And now we have that floor
portion that we're going to add some
really cool materials to as well. And
we're done with the modeling portion of
this tutorial. We can go ahead and set
up materials. So I'm going to get a set
material node and put one on each of
these final lines. This one
corresponding with the flat portion. So
let's go to the material portion,
material side. Let's get new and call it
flat. Let's add that there. We're going
to get another one. Call it
wire. And then you can see where it says
curve to mesh, mesh to curve. Just add
the wire material. And then we can just
call this one
cubes. They're all going to have the
same material. So we'll add that there.
So now we are ready to move on over to
the shading. So I'm going to switch this
window to the shader editor. And note up
here where you can grab your materials.
So I'm going to go to cycles. You can
also render this in EV if you're more
comfortable in that engine. Um we're
going to be using cycles for all of
these materials. So, what I'm going to
do here is grab the flat material first.
I'm going to give it a black color. On
emission, I'm going to give it a red and
give it a strength of like three and
make the roughness really, really low.
So, now we get this shiny emissive
floor, which is really going to make
this just look really awesome. Next
thing I want to do is when go over to
the wire, I'm actually going to go hover
over here and hit C. I'm going to grab
the wire and do the same exact thing.
Roughness, low, emission. I'm going to
paste that there and give it a strength
of three. So, now we have these emissive
wireframes. Now, for the fun part, one
of the fun parts really, is getting
these cubes to look really cool. So,
let's bring the metallic up. We'll bring
the color somewhere over here. And we're
going to play with roughness first. So,
we're going to get a mix color cuz we're
going to combine two materials. This is
one of my favorite ways to make an
interesting sci-fi material. So, let's
go ahead and get in a
noise texture. If you have the node
wrangler add-on enabled, I'm going to
hit CtrlT, get the object coordinate,
and plug factor into A. And I just want
to look at A. So, that's going to be to
the left. And we also need a color ramp.
So, let's bring this in. Bring that in.
We're starting to get something really
cool. I'm going to bring my detail to 12
and my roughness really high and then
just bring this down a bit. So, right
about now, I think is when I'm going to
pick my composition and my lighting cuz
the lighting is going to greatly affect
the decisions that I'm going to make
with the shading, especially with
roughness and reflection. So, I want to
set up my lighting now. So, that means I
also want to set up my camera view.
So
maybe something like that.
That's a pretty cool angle. Yeah. All
right.
Creates this big red channel so we can
appreciate details. And also there's
going to be a lot of other details here
that uh are missing with the small
objects. So I'm going to bring a render
region in. And then we're going to go
here to the normal lights and let's get
an area light going. So, I want the
lighting
to come in. If we're looking at the
camera, I want the lighting to hit this
direction.
So, I'm going to switch this light over
to a disc.
Hit R twice.
Going to scale it up a little bit.
Bring that brightness up. I'm going to
bring that spread in a little bit
because what I want is some areas of
contrast. And actually, we're going to
make this light smaller.
What I want is some points of contrast
where the light is uh not quite as
present.
So, we'll just shrink him a little bit.
We're make make him a lot darker and
we're going to make him a light green.
Okay. So, now we can go back to looking
at our materials because now the light
you can see, you can't really tell the
details here, but you can see details
here. So that is uh the big reason we
want to set up our lighting now. And all
of our lighting decisions
greatly affect what's going on here.
So we're going to get this roughness
pretty high. So I'm going to bring this
in. So notice we can start to make out
these details
in the noise texture
like that. Now let's go ahead and make
another pattern. So we're going to get a
voronoi.
We're going to plug vector here. I'm
going to go from uklitian to chbbyev.
And we're going to go to F2.
Let's get a color ramp as well. I'm just
going to highlight these and hit G to
move them back. And let's plug
everything here. And then let's bring
that factor over so we can just look at
that. So we see this really cool
pattern. I'm going to bring the scale
up quite a bit. Let's bring this Let's
bring the color ramp in so we can see
more of these details. And then
if we zoom in here and we play with the
detail slider, there's a lot of really
cool
details we can now have access to and
make something really cool with. So
that's pretty cool and detailed. So then
if you bring this factor to the middle,
you can mix the roughness, you can see
with the noise. So you get this nice
combination of the two. So we like that.
and it really highlights over here. So
now we have like the roughness portion.
We have some interesting details here,
especially in the highlights. But let's
go ahead and get a bump node so we can
start to get some more void voronoi
patterns that actually interact with the
lighting. So if I plug bump into normal,
we're just going to get a brand new
voroi texture. Plug that vector right
into there. And then plug color into
height. And you're not going to see
much. If this is your first time dealing
with this new update, play with the
filter width, and that's going to make
those cracks a lot more visible. So,
we're going to go to chvy,
bring the scale up on this one, and
again, bring up that filter width, and
you're going to get a more dramatic look
on that pattern. And that's what we're
looking for there. And then what I want
to do, we're going to get a mix color,
and we're going to mix two different
patterns together. So, I'm going to
bring the factor over to the right and
get I'm going to hit control shift D.
Get a brand new Voronoi. And I hit
control shift D so that it plugs that
mapping into the vector. What I want to
do now is just bring up the scale. We're
going to go to an F2. And then again,
you can play with that detail to get
more or less detail depending on how you
want it to look. So now we have on the
mix this
and that. And here's a really cool trick
I really love to do with Voronoi is I'm
going to get a color ramp.
Switch this color ramp to uh constant so
there's no soft gradient between these
two details and this Voro texture with
the big scale the with the value of 2.1.
Plug that right into there and then plug
this into the factor and it's going to
segment out
where that really detailed section is
going to show up. And then you can just
go to a 4D and play with a seed value of
where that is going to be. Actually,
this is really cool right here actually.
So, we can just play around. So, this is
really nice. It's We have some really
cool detail. In fact, I think the filter
is really strong. I think I'm going to
bring that down. Okay, cool. So, now we
have this. What I want to do now is to
play around with a little bit of
emission on this material as well.
So we can get some light in these really
highly detailed portions. So what we're
going to do is we're going to get
another mix color. We're going to make
this one black. We're going to get a
color ramp.
Plug that into B and make this that red.
So what we're going to do going to bring
that color back up.
Make that red. And let's plug this color
with the really high scale into there.
So now you can see
that happening.
And then we're going to plug this color
ramp right into the factor. And it's
going to isolate that emission to those
spots with the really cool high detail.
And so now what I'm going to do is I'm
just going to switch this from linear to
constant and decide how much light
I want in this scene. And there we go.
Now we have all of this working
together. and looking really cool. Now,
let's deal with the
flat portion of this tutorial. So, let's
go ahead and get another mix color for
here. This is probably my favorite part
of this tutorial. So, let's get this mix
color here. Plug that there. We'll get a
color ramp.
Plug that on the bottom and make this
portion black and this part of the color
ramp a nice red just like we've been
dealing with. So, what we're going to do
now is get a wave texture and then get a
CtrlT
mapping setup and plug that here. So,
I'm going to switch this over to Y and
then bring that keep that scale
something like this. And now, let's go
ahead get another color ramp and another
wave texture. And we're going to make
something really cool. Let's plug
mapping here, color here, and then color
into the factor. and it's going to make
this really cool looking scene. So, what
I can do here on the color ramp is I'm
going to copy this color just by hitting
Ctrl + C, click that, Ctrl +V, and then
bringing that down. And then I'm just
going to bring the scale up, bring the
scale down on this.
And you get this really interesting
color variation. And so now it's going
to leave you with multiple ways to
animate with the phase offset. So you
can animate the location phase offset
there and the phase offset here. And it
does create this really interesting kind
of visually makes it look like it widens
and shrinks. Now that's cool. I do want
even more detail in this color. I want
more variation. And rather than doing
that through color, we can do that
through strength of emission. So what we
can do is get a map range instead of a
color ramp. The reason why we're using a
map range cuz I want to deal with values
and not uh I want to use numerical
values and not color values so that we
can be a little bit more uh exact and
have some some control. And then I'm
going to get a voronoi texture with its
own mapping setup cuz we want to be able
to manipulate that here. And then we'll
plug color right into value. It's going
to do that. And then I'm going to switch
this to
chby and stretch it out
like this.
And then we can play with that minimum
and that maximum to provide
even more
detail on the ground portion which again
provides another opportunity for
animation. I didn't animate it in mine
but that's you can totally do it in
yours. Now notice this really hard edge
that the voroi is creating. I don't
prefer that. So, I'm going to go here to
a smooth F1. I'm going to bring that
smoothness down to bring it back to
where it was. And then just smoothen a
little bit. What I want is just a little
bit more
uh brightness variation. Cuz if we just
have nothing, we have this still cool
but boring kind of wave. If we add this,
it just brings an extra level of detail
that I really, really like. And then
what I'm going to do is just go ahead
and even out
some colors here.
And there we go. Now your maximum
emission is right here on the two max in
case you kind of lose it. And then here
on the wireframe, we're just going to
bring that brightness up a little bit
too.
So let's go back to geometry nodes and
I'm going to go here on this value. I'm
just going to plug this value right here
into the density. It's going to bring
all those guys back and now we can look
at it in the layout. So this is our
scene. Last thing I want to do, bring
the world to black. Go to my volume and
give it a principled volume node and
just give a little bit of volume into
the scene. It's hard to pull to make
out. So what I'm going to do to give
this a little bit more style is put a
point light right over here.
So I'm going hit shift A.
So, I'm going to hit shift A, get a
point light, hit G, and move it over
here, and then give it a brightness of
like 800. That's 8,000.
And then make it a nice red. And so that
is going to conflict with this green
light over here that I'm going to
saturate a little bit more.
There we go. So now the volume is going
to feel a little bit more full. This
whole scene is going to feel a little
bit better. So, I'm going to render this
once and we can see how this looks. And
here we have it, our final piece.
There's a lot of little details that you
can go back and refine. Uh, it feels
obviously with the tutorials you're
running and running, but take your time
and adjust things like the size of the
wireframe, how the roughness looks, how
bright things are, the lighting,
everything can be improved with designs
like this. You can have a lot of fun
with it. But this is the full idea and
that's how you do it. So, there you go.
That's how you create this really
beautiful render. a lot of really cool
things that you can apply to other
designs and other renders. Again, if you
want to check out that full series on my
Patreon, you can check it out. You can
check it out linked in the description.
And with that being said, I'll see you
guys in the next