All right, this video is about particle
systems in geometry nodes. I want to
show you a ton of different ways that we
can first set them up, uh, get them
shaped to really cool stuff, animating
in really, really cool ways. A lot of it
is really not that complicated. You
don't need to be an expert or super
proficient in geometry nodes to do some
of these things. So, I'm going to show
you how to get them to be shaped in ways
that you want them for your ideas. I'm
going to show you different ways to
animate them and control the movements
so it doesn't really feel like you're
kind of at the mercy of textures and
things like that. And I want to show you
how to get them to look good, like
changing different object variations,
scales, textures, lighting. I'm going to
be showing five different animations
throughout this video as references to
what I'm talking about. If you want all
of the tutorials for all five of those,
those are available on my Patreon right
now under the particles collection. So,
you can check out all of those. And this
animation in particular is completely
free for non-members as well. So if you
want to check that out and watch the
rest of them, that is available linked
in the description. And you can also get
a uh discount if you subscribe annually.
So with that being said, let's learn how
to make cool particle systems. Okay,
let's start with like the super basic
stuff just just right now and then we'll
very quickly get into some cool stuff.
So first just open up two windows. We're
going to throw in any piece of geometry
and then I'm going to switch this to the
geo node editor. I'm going to click new.
So there's two ways to get particles
available in your scene. It's you can
either distribute them on something or
in something. So I'll use that idea with
an icosphere. So scale it up, subdivide
it. You could first do a distribute
points on faces and it's going to
randomly place points all over any
geometry you put in geometry notes. That
be letters, logos, any any geometry you
can put it on it like it's a shell. or
again taking any piece of geometry, you
can convert it into a volume and you can
do a distribute points in volume and
that's of course going to put the
objects within the volume of whatever
you put it in. So if you're doing logos
and you want to turn the logo into
particles, this is how you do it. Now
when it comes to getting the very first
steps of any particle system idea, you
do have to figure out what is the
initial shape we have to go with to go
in that direction. So for this example,
this animation kind of looks like a
wreath. So the first thing I decided was
let's get a cylinder and uh distribute
points on that cylinder and that will
get us uh at the beginning of that then
I was able to later uh displace those
particles and get that more interesting
look. But I started with an initial uh
cylinder shape and distributed points on
it. Now with these animations that I
did, there was two ways that I
influenced the initial shape. So you can
place particles in or on some
predetermined shape like a circle, uh
flat plane, even text, logos, different
things like that. You can use that
initial shape and you can predetermine
that right there. Or you can use images
and textures to delete particles that
will influence how they will show up and
create some type of initial shape. So
that's typically one of the first things
you're going to want to be thinking
about when trying to make something
cool. So, in terms of using textures and
images to delete things, both of these
animations are doing the exact same
thing. Using images to delete points
that we can then later animate or do
something with. So, for example, I got a
cube and I just stretched it to be
basically the type of shape that I'm
wanting my particle system to be before
I start deleting points. And then again,
distributed those points within that
space. Once you have some kind of image
picked out, you'll get a delete
geometry. Get an image texture and open
up that image. Then you're going to need
some vector math and some position
information so that you can actually
move this thing around by adjusting the
X and the Y
of the text and then moving them around
with your ad. And that is how you can
get text to actually be deleting and
showing up. And then you can go after
that coloring and animating the points.
That is how we can actually delete
points using images, using textures, all
of that. And again, I did the exact same
thing with an image of a fingerprint.
So, you can use any solid black and
white image to influence particles. One
other random way that I was able to
influence the shape of the particles in
this particular animation was I just
wanted no matter what the animation was,
I wanted to contain what you were seeing
within a sphere. So, it was simple. I
just was able to get a proximity system
to say once particles go out a certain
distance scale them out and after that
it made this really really cool
animation. So once you have some kind of
initial shape that you've decided for
your particle system now we can actually
get into animating them moving them
around with textures and different
things like that to make them look and
move in a really cool way. So let's do
that. I want to start out with in my
opinion the the coolest way that I've
recently found to animate particles. So,
we just have a couple nodes putting
small particles in a system. Now, for
context, the way I've been animating
particles for a really long time was
getting the color into an offset and
then just getting a really small scale.
And then you can just play with the W.
And now we can actually move around and
animate particles just like this. You
can also get vector math to say how
strong do we want this effect to be. But
this is how I've been doing it from day
one. animating particles and geometry
nodes. But now we have this new thing
called a repeat zone. And I've been
seeing this technique float around on
the internet. Uh Mantisa did a really
cool live stream on it. And there's a
lot of cool things we can do with this.
So So if you put the set position within
a repeat and then do that same thing
that we just did, I'm going to go ahead
bring my scale to be something very,
very small. And once we start to repeat
this, you get this very interesting
almost splashy looking texture that if
we go ahead and play with the 4D, you
get something really really awesome. And
it is greatly affected by uh the scale
of your, you know, the vector scale that
we do and of course by the scale of the
texture. And we get something amazing.
If I bring down the scale of my points
and I just bring up the density of these
this animation, it just starts to look
absolutely incredible. We can bring up
the scale a little bit. If we bring down
the scale a little bit, gets it a little
bit more uh waterlike. Playing with the
W, playing with the scale. There's a ton
of things that you can do with this and
it just looks really really cool. So,
just repeating a noise texture get some
pretty insane particle uh textures. Now,
another thing we can do is if we have if
we have a noise texture at a really low
scale, just something like this. It's
kind of globby for whatever reason. This
is the animation and the shape you want
this to be. You can add a little bit of
detail by mixing another noise texture
with a mixed color. And then you can
take one noise texture, scale it up
pretty significantly, bring it back to
the original shape. And if you just
bring that factor in, it's just going to
give it a little bit more of a
interesting higher detailed shape rather
than this.
You can actually bring up the detail to
something like that.
And you have a little bit more variation
and also another opportunity to animate
two different components of the noise
texture of the particle system. And it
gives you a lot of control and a way to
just make something even more
interesting. getting all the individual
particles to look like they're moving
and the larger uh scene as well. One
more problem you might run into with
animating particles is you're animating
these particles at a really low scale
right here. It's 009 and all all the
particles are just kind of moving
together like a like a really close
together school of fish. See how that
looks? And we can just bring up that
scale a little bit. You get the idea
that all the particles don't look like
they have a mind of their own. They're
all moving kind of with the same mind
essentially. And I'm calling the mind
the W. They're all moving from the same
W value. I want them to have their own
mind. What could I do? I can bring up
the scale, right? Maybe something pretty
big so that it doesn't look like they're
all dealing with the same texture. Um,
then this W value gets very very
sensitive. I mean you can look but at a
smaller value like three the the W is a
is far more controlled. You can animate
it better but again all the points just
look like they're moving together. How
can we fix that? So before the set
position you can get a store named
attribute a random value node and we'll
just plug that value into value and just
call it R. Now we can get a named
attribute node. Call that and then plug
attribute right into the W because again
the problem is they're all animating
from the same W value. Now we're going
to randomize the W value per point. Now
we'll get a math node and set it to
multiply add. This add right here is the
W value. It's just now we have access to
it through the addendant and the
multiplier is just going to strengthen
that effect per point. And now all of
the objects are still animating from a
very small noise texture scale, but they
all are doing their own thing. And
again, this add is the W. So if you know
how to loop the W, just do it right
here. And then now you have a collection
of points that are at a low scale value,
but all have a mind of their own. This
was one of my favorite animations I did.
And it really has this incredible nebula
look. So, the way I was able to set that
up was again using that cylinder like I
mentioned, getting a bunch of particles
and then displacing them using that
repeat zone trick, but instead of
animating the particles with the W
value, I just created that vector math
kind of mapping setup and then I
actually rotated the texture. So, as
that texture is slowly rotating, those
particles are technically not moving
from a set position standpoint. They're
just being affected by the fact that
that texture is moving and they're kind
of moving like it's water. This really
cool nebula look. So instead of
animating the W, maybe try rotating the
texture of the noise and seeing how
those particles react. So you can
animate the W. You can also animate the
rotation as another way to get some
really cool motion. All right. As a
beginner, I think lighting particles is
incredibly frustrating. I'm typically
finding myself in two different uh kind
of lighting environments. This kind of
low light, very high contrast
environment or a much brighter
environment that's a little bit more
delicate when it comes to how we're
placing lights. Now, in either of these
two environments, the biggest thing that
is going to affect how professional or
how good it's going to look is just
having more particles, especially if the
particles are small. I found myself
bringing my density up to a point where
it almost felt like it was a solid
object. And at that point, that's when
the lighting started to work in my
favor. If you have too few particles,
the light is just going to go straight
through it. It's not going to be dense
enough, and it's really not going to be
readable, and the lighting is really
going to struggle. So, sometimes the
answer is simple as bring up your
density of the particles. I know it's
very computer inensive. Just figure out
what number that looks like, and then
when you're ready to render, bring it up
to that number, render out your
animation. So, I'll give you an example.
In this scene right here, there was
three lights. I took my background far
back enough to where the area lights
that were going to hit the particles
weren't hitting my background. And I was
able to control the background
independently. Then I was able to get a
light above it and then a light at the
very back hitting the back of it to get
it this really nice studio effect where
my background had its own control
independently to make it look really
beautiful. And then two points at the
top and the back to make it look really,
really nice. Now, of course, sometimes
the lighting comes from the particles
themselves because the particles are
emissive. So, in that case, lighting
isn't really going to affect it, and you
can get away with lower densities
because things are a little bit easier
to read. All right, now let's talk about
shading and shaping these particles so
they can look really cool. Now, most of
the time, I'm just using the default
spherical points that happen when you
just simply add points. Now, one trick
I've recently used is separating some of
the objects and replacing them with this
flat circle that has a really reflective
metallic material. That's going to
create these really reflective moments
that add just this really nice interest
to your animation. So, you don't always
have to stick with the default spheres.
Another really easy way to add some
interest in your animation is just
simply randomizing the size of the
points. Then, what you can do is set up
a store named attribute. plug that same
randomization into the attribute. You
can go to the shading, call that
attribute and plug that into the shading
so that you can also get random color in
your animations and they stay put when
the particles are moving around, which I
think is really important. Now, using
that same idea of taking something in
geometry nodes, plugging it into a store
named attribute, you can actually take
the same noise texture that is operating
some movements in geometry nodes, and
you can send that into the shading and
use that to texture the points as well.
I was actually able to take that idea
and plug that texture into some of the
brightness of those particles in this
animation, and I just think it made it
look much, much cooler. So, there you
go. Those are all of my tips and tricks
that I dove into this week to make some
really cool animations. Again, if you
want the step-by-step tutorials for
those animations, they are available on
Patreon right now. And this one is uh
totally free, so you can check that one
out as well. So, with that being said, I
hope you learned some really cool things
and I will see you in the next