How's it going, guys? So, in this
tutorial, we are going to be creating
this animation right here. It's going to
be super fun and pretty easy. First
thing we're going to do is hop into
geometry nodes and create some
displacement and shape it to look more
like hills. After that, I'll show you
how to mirror displacement in geometry
nodes. And that's going to allow us to
create our camera and make a looping
animation with the displacement. Then,
we're going to hop into the shading, and
I'm going to show you a simple way to
make a really nice stepped gradient
effect. Then we're going to combine two
different wave textures to create a
really nice animated line effect. We're
going to solidify that topographic map
inspiration and create a grid floor for
the bottom and we'll be done. This
animation is part of a series of
tutorials here on YouTube that are
inspired by topographic map art and
animations. I'll be posting four of
these tutorials backtoback here on
YouTube. So, if you want to learn more
of this stuff, you can go and check out
the other ones like this. They're all
really cool and there's a lot of fun
things to learn. On Patreon, I posted
what I'm calling the topographic
blueprint, which is an hour and 20
minutes of training of all the shading,
geometry nodes, and animation tricks
that are combined to make these four
animations and many others. Here on
YouTube, all those elements are combined
to make really cool animations. But on
Patreon, I'm showing you every
individual effect and tip and trick so
that you can combine them and make your
own original topographic map inspired
animations. So, if you want to check
that out, that is going to be linked in
the description and you can get a
discount if you subscribe annually. With
that being said, let's get into this
tutorial. All right, so we are going to
go ahead and I'm going to hop into the
Geometry Notes workspace and just delete
these windows. Just get it how I like
it. Let's get a plane. Let's call it
just going to call it geo. We're going
to build the displacement and the tiling
uh directly in geometry nodes. So, it
should be really fun. So, we're going to
click new. Let's go ahead and delete
this. We're going to go ahead and get a
get a grid. And then we're going to plug
this right into here. And we're going to
make it 40x 40. Really big. Uh really
it's like 20 by 20. Then we can make the
vertices at about
300 by 300. And that's going to give us
a nice amount of subdivision for nice
smooth displacement. So, speaking of
displacement, we're going to get a set
position node. Let's get a
going to get a combined XYZ node. And
we're going to plug a noise texture
right into the Z. So, let's plug factor.
Let's put color. We're going to switch
to heterotrain and bring that scale up
pretty nicely. And then let's get a
vector math node.
This vector math node is going to allow
us to adjust the strength of the
displacement. So, if we bring it all the
way down here to scale, we can do
something like this. Now, I need some
flat portions to give it that that uh
topographic map uh look. So, the way
we're going to do that is with a RGB
curves node. So, get an RGB curves node.
We're going to zoom in here. We're going
to add just a point right about here and
a point here and a point here. And then
bring this up. And that's going to
flatten it uh pretty dramatically. So we
can bring this down like that
until we have some flat portions. But it
doesn't need to be super super flat.
What I don't want is things jutting down
too far cuz if we do this, see that? So
we're kind of killing
that effect. And then we can bring the
scale back up. And then obviously we can
bring the uh scale of the noise however
we want that to look. And we can adjust
this um plenty later. Let's get a
set shade smooth node. And we're going
to go ahead
and actually I'm going to highlight
these, hit G, and get more space. Let's
go ahead and tile our uh displacement so
that this loop uh this animation can
loop seamlessly. So what we're going to
do is get a transform geometry node.
a join geometry node and then plug the
set position into the join and this guy
is now a duplicate. So we can go I know
this guy is 40 by 40. So if I just go
ahead and move this on the Y or the X by
40,
it is going to bring it exactly one
space over. And if we chose to move it
on the X, let's go here on the X scale
and give it -1. And that creates a
mirror that we can then tile this. So
let's go ahead and get another transform
geometry node
and another join geometry and plug the
join into the join. Again, he is a
duplicate. So then we can bring this
down. And looks like it needs to be
what? 80. Yeah, 80 on the X. And now we
have
something that is uh going to be able to
once we run the camera down loopable
seamlessly. So let's go ahead and
actually animate that camera. So I'm
just going to position my viewport
wherever I want the relative camera
position to be. So something like this.
We'll go right about here. I'm going hit
shift A and then get a uh if I can find
it camera control alt0 we'll snap it to
view
and then I'm going to hit the tilda key
and I'm going to look at the position of
my camera. He needs to be at the very
edge of this geometry here. So I know my
camera needs to be moving on the X and
so looks like it needs to be -20
because that's how big this is. This is
40x 40 which means in kind of real space
it's 20 by 20. So now I can look at my
camera and we can go ahead and animate.
So first I'm just going to go ahead
click on my camera going to rotate it a
little bit.
Something like that. And then I'm going
to hit and then I'm going to zoom it in
a little bit on the millimeters so that
all of my geometry is filling my screen.
So let's go ahead and create this
animation. I'm going to give myself
600 frames. I'm going to go back to
frame one and make sure in your
preferences in the animation, your
default interpolation is linear. So, we
can look at this from the tilt key uh
the top view here. I'm looking at my
camera. We'll go to the settings here.
Make sure you are again at frame zero.
Right here on the X, make sure he is at
20.
Hit the key frame and go to the very end
to frame 600. And I know that he needs
to be
see this seam right here. Skip this
seam. And you need to stop it at this
seam. So I'm going to go back to my
camera and just eyeball that. So I'm
going to go ahead hold down control and
go all the way to that seam, which is
going to be 60. So if you just want to
type in, go to the end of your timeline,
type in 60, hit the key frame, you are
going to be exactly where you need to
be. So, I'm going to bring my We can see
we can see. Let's make sure this loops
seamlessly. So, once he gets to the end
and restarts, it will look seamless. So,
I'm going to press play.
Go to the end. Perfect. This is a
perfect seamless loop. So, now we can
focus on uh the shading of this
animation. So, I'm going to bring my
detail down a little bit on these hills
and maybe flatten a few things out here.
Something like this.
Bring my scale up.
Bring my strength up. There we go. Have
a little bit of fun. So, let's go ahead
and add some shading. So, right over
here, let's go ahead and get a shader, a
emission, and then we can go over here,
get a
set material node, and grab that. And
then let's head over to shading. I'm
going to go ahead and get my windows the
way I want them to be. So, this one
being the 3D viewport, this one being
the shader editor. So, first let's go
ahead and let's get a color ramp. Plug
this into here. I'm going to hit I'm
going to hit CtrlT. I'm going to go over
the factor I mean over the image texture
and use the object coordinate. And then
I'm going to get a separate XYZ and I'm
going to define it to the Z so that we
can start to see this uh gradient
working. Next thing I want to do, you
can also, you can control it here.
What I want to do before the color ramp
is get a map range. And the map range is
going to give us a really cool effect.
So, I'm going to go here, go from linear
to stepped linear. And that's going to
give us these really cool steps that we
can use uh to make this look really
awesome. Now if you want to move the
gradient up, you can get another math
node
and use the value to bring it up like
that.
You can bring it down. So all it's all
completely up to you. Here in the color
ramp, you can go ahead and define
whatever color you want this to be. So
we're going to go ahead and say maybe
maybe a nice green. Something like this.
And then this black portion is going to
be transparency. So let's go ahead and
get in a mix shader. Get a transparent
BSDF. Plug that here. And you're going
to see this really grainy transparency.
So here in the camera uh the camera
icon, I'm going to go here to Eevee.
Back to shading. You're going to see
dithered. Blended is going to give you
that nice smooth um transparency. Now
we'll put our world brightness to black.
And then we can throw some stuff here on
the bottom. But now we can go ahead and
say get another color ramp
and define our transparency. So plug
plug the map range into the color a ramp
and the color a ramp into the factor.
And then we're going to flip the color
ramp. So now what's under this is going
to be transparent. You can kind of see
it working. You can see through. The
darker it is, the more you can see
through it. So that's great. Now you'll
notice how it's like all white up here.
There's no definition. You can take the
from max and bring it up a little bit
and that is going to allow a little bit
more um a little bit more I can't think
of the word not great with words today.
Uh but it's going to help with that
scale and that really interesting
stepped look and not look so flat on the
tops. Now let's go and add those
blinking lines that are in the
animation. And so we're going to go
ahead get another mix shader and we're
going to get a emission node. And I'm
just going to go ahead and click on
this. Hit Ctrl + C on this color. Ctrl
+V on that color. Plug it here. And
let's go ahead and get in a color ramp
to create this. We're going to get a
wave texture. And then we're going to
get a brand. We're going to hit control
T and get a brand new set of mapping
nodes. Plug color here. And then we're
going to switch from X to Z. and it's
going to create this really interesting
effect. We're going to we're going to go
from linear to constant.
But to make these lines even thinner,
you can switch this over to saw. And
that's going to allow a little bit more
of a thin uh line look. And then you can
just bring this up to see how many lines
you want to to do. You can get it to
line up with the steps. Um you don't
have to obviously, but whatever you want
to do, you can absolutely do. So you
have this. Now remember, we can play
with this thickness. So let's go ahead.
We have the lines. I want to get them uh
to be blinking in and out on the
scene. So one thing I want to do is
bring the emission strength down on the
emi on this emission node down here so
that we can see all of the lines and the
lines being the brightest part of this
animation. So here's a really really fun
trick that I showed uh here on YouTube a
while back. We're going to take this.
I'm going to get a mix color.
So, this is plugged into A. I'm going to
hit control shift D. Again, that works
if you have the node wrangler add-on
enabled or just plug the wave texture
into a new color ramp of a duplicate of
this one. Plug it into here. So, here on
this factor, I'm going to bring these
lines to be as thin as possible on the
color ramp. Bring the factor to the
right. And we'll just make them a little
thicker.
And then, let's get another color ramp.
I'm hit shift D and bring it to the
middle. Control shift D on this wave
texture just so that he's still plugged
into the mapping. Plug it into there and
then plug him into the factor. Once we
get a smaller scale, so maybe 0.5,
you're going to get this difference in
thickness. And so it's using a wave
texture to mask out um some of the
thicker lines and the thinner lines. So
you can have some fun
with that. And it's really really cool.
If you go to the compositing, I'm click
use nodes. I'm going get a glare node
set to fog glow. We'll go back to
shading. And I'm going to hit this and
click on always. What's going to happen
is we can bring up when we get this
emission node here. I'm going to bring
up the brightness so that the thicker
ones are going to glow.
Then you play with the phase offset. And
now you have this. Now, one thing I want
to do is eliminate some of the lines
down here. So, it's still topographic
map looking. How am I going to do that?
So, I'm going to hit G and move these
over. This emission node is handling the
lines. So, what I want to do is just get
another mix shader. So, I'm going to
give myself a little bit more space here
just so it because it's going to start
getting a little wild. We're going to
get another transparent BSDF. You could
just plug this one over here, but just
to keep things visually in a good spot,
I'm going to just get a new transparent
node. What I want to do, I give myself
some more space here, is get a color
ramp
so we can plug something into it. What I
want to plug into it is the map range
that is creating this gradient because
we want to use a gradient to say kill
some of these uh lines down here.
So, I'm going to plug the map range
into the color ramp. And then I'm just
going to flip the color ramp. And as you
can see, once we move the white one, it
removes some of those. I'm going to use
a constant offset so it's a little bit
more precise.
I just want like that big one on the
bottom gone. So now when we go back to
this top wave texture,
it looks a little better in my opinion.
So there we go. We are pretty much done
with this animation. One thing I want to
do
is get a grid floor
so it looks like that classic
topographic maps uh vibe. So I'm going
to get a plane and I'm going to hit S20.
Hit control A, apply that scale. Then
I'm going to hit Alt D holding down
control and snapping each one to the
edge. Alt D, holding down control, snap
it to the edge. Alt D.
There we go. So now I'm going to take
this, bring it up so that the the plane
isn't connecting to the bottom. Select
this bottom plane. Now the reason why we
did alt D is when we add a material to
this plane, it's going to add it to
those planes, too, because they are
instances. So let's head back to
shading. I'm going to click new. I'm
going hit period to bring up that
principled emission. We're just going to
give it a strength of like three. So
yep, we can see it through our
mountains.
Let's get a color ramp.
plug it here. And then I'm going to
click on the mountains. I'm just going
to copy this color. And then click back
on this bottom plane, paste it there.
We're going to get a Voronoi texture.
Hit CtrlT. And use the object coordinate
distance here. Bring the randomness in.
And we're going to go from uklidian to
chvy.
Bring that scale to like
three. We're going to go from linear to
constant.
Where's our grid? There it is. And then
we're going to try to make our grid as
thin
as possible. There we go. And what I
like to do
is actually I'm going to se select all
of these planes by holding down shift
and I'm going to bring them down so that
there's a parallax effect. So I'm going
to bring them over. So when I press
play,
you can see it kind of looks like the
mountains are moving faster than that
bottom grid. So it's going to create
this really, really cool, quite subtle
parallax effect. And then I'm just going
to bring down the brightness of the grid
on the bottom.
And now if I press play,
it has this really cool effect. Last
thing we need to do is animate
the phase offset here. So, I'm going to
give myself a timeline.
I have 600 frames.
So, I'm just going to give myself some
space for this timeline. Go back to
frame zero. And to get the phase offset
of a wave texture to loop, you have to
use pi. So, if you've never done it,
it's extremely easy. Hit I, go to the
very end, and I'm going to type in 10.
You need to use an even number. 10 times
or asterisk pi.
And that's really slow. So I'm going to
do maybe
30 asterisk pi. Hit I.
There we go.
And we now have
in fact let's make it even faster. So
we'll do I don't know
40 asterisk pi
hit I
and then I'm going to play with the
scale.
The smaller the value of the wave, the
smoother this effect is going to look.
So like this is pretty cool and
dramatic.
And I
I think this is really really really
cool.
And this is how you create this
animation. Super fun, super cool, super
easy. What we can do now is just go
ahead and export it. So, I'm going to
use 1920 x 1080. I highly recommend
using a PNG sequence. Just pick a
folder. Just pick your folder, send it
in there, and uh compile it. If you
don't want to do that, you can do FFmpeg
video encoding to MP4 or QuickTime if
you're on Mac. and then medium quality
to perceptually lossless render render
animation. And when you're done, you'll
have something really cool like mine.
So, thank you for watching. Again, if
you want to check out that hour 20
minute long video on my Patreon showing
you all the different ways to combine
things and all kind of the blueprint of
making these really cool topographic map
inspired animations, you can check that
out. That is linked in the description
and you can get all these project files.
So, hope you guys enjoyed it and I will
see you in the next