How's it going? So, in today's tutorial,
we're going to be making this animation.
It's honestly one of my favorite I've
done in a really long time. First thing
we're going to do is duplicate a bunch
of curves and make sure that they are
sitting in the right position. So, this
animation is going to loop. Then, we're
going to go ahead and displace the
curves and shape that displacement to
look more like a topographic map. Then,
we're going to go ahead and parent a
gradient to the camera movement, which
is going to create the animation. Then,
we're going to go ahead and edit that
gradient to create a really cool glowing
effect. And then after that, we're going
to use a wave texture to select the
center curves to make them brighter and
create a really nice focal point. Then
we're going to make a simple metallic
floor material, and we'll be totally
done. This animation is part of a series
of tutorials here on YouTube that are
inspired by topographic map art and
animations. I'll be posting four of
these tutorials back toback here on
YouTube. So, if you want to learn more
of this stuff, you can go and check out
the other ones like this. They're all
really cool and there's a lot of fun
things to learn. On Patreon, I posted
what I'm calling the topographic
blueprint, which is an hour and 20
minutes of training of all the shading,
geometry nodes, and animation tricks
that are combined to make these four
animations and many others. Here on
YouTube, all those elements are combined
to make really cool animations. But on
Patreon, I'm showing you every
individual effect and tip and trick so
that you can combine them and make your
own original topographic map inspired
animations. So, if you want to check
that out, that is going to be linked in
the description, and you can get a
discount if you subscribe annually. With
that being said, let's get into this
tutorial. All right, I'm going to start
uh and make my windows. So, I'm just
going to go down in this, go up on that.
I like my geometry nodes and my shading
to be the same uh this ways. You can do
however you want. There really is no
technical benefit to doing either way.
This is just what I preferably, this is
my preference. Let's head into geometry
nodes. First, let's hit shift A. Get a
plane. I'm going to title this geo. You
don't have to title it. Title it
whatever you want. And we're going to
click new here in geometry nodes.
Delete. Shift A. And we're going to
search a grid. And we're going to plug
this right into here. We're delete that.
I'm going to hit shift A and get a
quadratic bezier. Plug that here. Let's
do a couple edits here. So, one is a
resolution of 300. And we are going to
go ahead click and drag here. Hit zero.
And then on the Y we're going to give it
a scale of 10. And that is going to
stretch it uh by essentially five units
here, 10 units here, 10 uh 10 m. And uh
we're happy with that. Now I want to do
uh some duplicates down the line of this
quadratic resier. the way I'm going to
make my array. Typically, if I'm
displacing immediately after uh making
the array, I like to use a simulation
zone for it. So, we're going to get a
simulation and we're going to plug here,
plug there, and then I'm just going to
bring it down. Let's go ahead and get a
I'm going to get a set position node, a
join geometry, and then plug the curve
into the join geometry. Just like that.
I want to move it by
13 this direction. Now, when I press
play, it is going to give me a bunch of
duplicates. And I believe 77 is the
amount that I wanted to go with. Then,
once you're done, you can go ahead and
get a bake node and bake it. And you're
all set. Now, I'm going to go ahead get
another set position node
just to move it to the center of where
I'll be working, using my camera, all of
that, just to keep everything uh in this
loop working correctly. So, I'm going to
go ahead on the X and the Y and do a
negative five. And that is just going to
plop it exactly where I'd want it to be.
Now, we can get our set position node
that is going to create our actual
displacement. So, let's get a another
set position node. We're going to get a
combine XYZ node. Plug that into the
offset. And let's plug a noise texture
into the Z. So, we'll get that noise.
Plug color into the Z. Now, we have some
displacement. I'm going to go ahead and
click on normalize. Give myself a scale
of 0.5. That looks really good. And then
let's get a vector math node so that we
can play with the strength of this
effect. We're going to click on scale.
And that is just going to be a scale
like a scale value here. So I'm just
going to keep it at one for now. And
what I don't want is if I look at here
from the uh right or the left, I want it
to kind of cut off. I want there to be
some flat portions. Right now it's like
all wave. I want some portions where it
goes down to look like the flat ground.
And so the way I can do that, the way I
prefer to do it, you can use color ramp.
That will just straight up crunch it
flat. That's not that fun. So we're
going to do a
RGB curves node. I'm going to add a
point here, here, here. And then the
part that's the most important, I'm
going to add a point right here in the
middle of this bottom square. Bring this
up. And that's going to create these
flat portions, but that aren't perfectly
flat. It's going to give you, maybe the
word nuance might be fun. It's going to
give you a little bit of nuance in the
flat portions, but not
completely kill um our ability to have
it more flat. And maybe we can bring it
down like this. Give it some more flat
areas. Um and then you can play with
that scale to give some parts that go
up. So now we have some flat parts that
are still a little bit wavy. And those
are really going to be pronounced once
we're playing with this animation some
more. So now we have this ready to go.
Now we are going to be making a looping
animation. And the biggest part of
making this loop is is uh the first and
the last frame needing to look exactly
the same so that this is a seamless
looping animation. The problem is if I
duplicate this tech this uh geometry
nodes
uh whatever we're going to call it uh
object you could see how you can see a
seam or you know a very obvious seam.
You can see how it does not connect from
one duplicate to the next. How can I
duplicate this texture but make it so
that it connects? Because if we can't do
that, this animation breaks. So what I
need to do is first mirror this
displacement. Then I can duplicate the
displacement. So what I can do is get a
transform geometry node and a join
geometry node and then plug this into
the join. Now we what we've done is made
a duplicate. So remember
we uh made this 10 this a scale of 10
which means here on the here on the Y if
I here on the Y if I move it down by 10
it's going to perfectly move it down
this direction and then here on the
scale if I do a negative one it is going
to flip that and now it mirrors our
displacement. There is a discernable
seam. It's not super obvious, especially
if you're just a viewer of the
animation. You're not looking for it.
Um, if this bothers you, there's really
not much you can do about it. But we now
have made uh a a mirror of this. So now
what I can do is get another
transfer uh transform geometry node,
join geometry, make another duplicate,
and move this guy down by 20. Now, we
can just literally duplicate, duplicate,
duplicate, and this is a seamless
pattern. So, that's what we're that's
what I wanted to make in order for this
animation to loop seamlessly. So, now
let's go ahead and give this a little
bit of geometry. So, I'm going to do a
curve to mesh
and a curve
circle. Uh just to keep this a little
bit lighter, I'm going to do a
resolution of uh four, a radius of 0005,
and then I'm going to plug this right
into the profile curve. Now we have some
actual geometry we can add a material
to, which is uh this is going to be a
great time to start adding materials. So
we're going to get a set material node.
We're going to go here to the shading,
create a material, and then grab it
right here. You can even name it
And you can see that's the uh that's the
material we made. So what I can do right
now is before we create the material, I
want to get the camera moving because
the camera is going to affect the
shading. So let's let's do that. I'm
going to go ahead and show you guys my
method for kind of making sure loops
loop. So I know that I scaled this these
strings are 10 m long. So that means in
real space here if I hit S5 that is how
big our object our you know our
scene our object is and then we just
then we mirrored it right at there and
so our camera needs to go
uh the length of two of these cubes I
mean two of these planes. And if we do
that
it's going to loop. So, I'm going to go
ahead and just set up my camera view, my
camera angle, however I want it to be.
Something like this.
And then I'm get a camera control, alt0,
snap it to view. I like, if we go here
to the camera settings, a focal length
of 100. That really gives it this nice
flat view. And then I'm just going to
tighten my view in a little bit till all
the strings are within view. Now, what I
can do is I'm going hit the tilda key
and go to the top. I'm actually also
going to take I'm going to delete this
just to make sure you guys know what's
going on. Take this plane and hit alt d.
That is going to create an instance. And
then hold down control and that is going
to snap everything. I neglected to say
that. Make sure that you are snapping
and then hitting alt d. And I'm hit alt
d again. And so what happens is when I
add a material to him, it'll add a
material to these instances that I just
created. So again, holding down control
so that this animation will perfectly
loop. And so now what I'm going to do is
I'm hit the tilt key, go to the top, and
the camera needs to start exactly on
this line here at the very very exact
edge of this uh cube, which is the exact
edge of this geometry node scene. So I
know that it needs to be
five. You can kind of see this thicker
line right here coinciding with that.
So, let's cut our let's get our
animation. So, I'm going to hit the back
arrow and then hit the back arrow again
on my keyboard to go to frame zero. And
then you can double check in your
animation preferences. Your default
interpolation is linear. That is going
to ensure a perfect loop. I'm going to
give myself 400 frames. Let me start my
camera at -5. I'm going to bring my uh
cursor to 400. I don't think cursor was
the right word. I'm going hold down
control, bring it all the way to the
edge of this second plane right here.
And you can double check. If it says 15,
you're in the right place. And now,
if I press play, let's watch the
animation. And uh wow, it's really slow.
Now, if I press play,
that's very, very slow, which is weird.
That didn't happen when I rehearsed
this. If it is really slow, you're not
getting any good playback, it's lagging
out. Um, what you can do is go back to
geometry nodes and get a
reample curve node. And I'll just plop
it right before the curve to mesh. And
that's going to just bring make your
essentially your curves low poly. And it
should Okay. Yeah. So that'll make your
scene a little bit lighter. You could
remove that later. And so now we have
this. If we just watch the animation
play through all the way to the end. So
we'll just wait around. We're just going
to double check that this animation is
going to loop seamlessly. So, we're
watching
and then once we get to the edge, just
pay attention. Okay, loop seamlessly.
400 to zero. So, now we have that, we
can go ahead and start working on our
shading
because the camera's going, like I said,
the camera is going to heavily affect
the shading. So, I'm going to go back to
geometry nodes and I'm going to mute
that uh
that reample curve node.
So, we can go here now to the shading.
And we have that material that we
labeled dude for no reason. Um, and then
you can create this in EV or cycles. So,
I'm just going to design this in EV. I'm
going to personally render this in
cycles cuz it just looks better. So, I'm
going to go down here and give myself an
emission strength of three. We can now
see this um this object. Now, I'm going
to go ahead get my color ramp, plug it
into the color, and I'm going to plug it
into the alpha.
Let's get a
gradient texture. And if you have the
node wrangler add-on enabled, comes with
Blender by default. Just hit control T
or get a mapping node and a texture
coordinate node and plug in the object.
And then plug color into color ramp. and
you're going to see this gradient
working. Now, in Eevee, see how it's
like this noisy transparency. You can go
here to the material settings and go
from dithered to blended. And that's
going to give you sort of that OG Eevee
looking uh transparency. And then here
on the rotation, I'm going to do a
rotate it by 90
so that it it's going the right
direction that I want. So, one thing we
need to do, I'm going hit shift A and
get an empty plane axis. What we're
going to do there is now I'm going to
click back on my uh curves and I'm going
to go over here to the object coordinate
and grab the empty. So, what's going to
happen now is when I click on my empty
and I move the empty around, that
controls the position of the gradient.
So, here's what's cool. I'm going to
click on the camera. I'm going hold down
shift, click on the empty. Crl P and
click on object. Now what's going to
happen is I'm hit this drop down, click
on my empty and just bring it forward a
little bit. When I press play,
that transparency is going to the
because the empty is mapped to the
camera. As this camera moves, it's going
to write or you know it kind of looks
like it's writing the geometry writing
these waves this sort of topographic map
vibe. So that is that is what I wanted.
So, that is how we create this really
cool effect. I'm going to go ahead and
make a uh timeline down here just for
me. Wherever it is.
So, now we can start making this look
really cool. So, go ahead and just click
on geo. We're going to go back here to
the the uh the color ramp. I'm going to
get a brand new node here. And then I'm
going to make it red so you guys can
kind of see the differentiation of what
what things are doing what.
This black portion is what we don't see
over here. It's the same thing that's
creating the alpha. So over here is
represented by this black node. And then
this white node is all the stuff behind
it. And this red one is obviously this
middle section. So what we can do
is I can just make it
a pure white. Make it the brightest
thing. And this make it that darker
portion. And then bring this in. Bring
this in. And I'm actually going to
switch it over to constant so that
there's no fade between the two.
And then I can just bring this in so we
have this one really bright section of
the curves. So that's how we create that
really cool effect. And then we can head
into the compositing. Turn on use nodes,
get a glare node, and turn on
fog glow. And then we can head back to
shading and then turn on always. And
that's how we get that glare. So you can
bring this up.
Just like that. So what I'm going to do
is bring this gray portion a little bit
brighter to be something right around
here.
And then let's do a really cool thing.
What I want to do is have a focal point
right here in the middle of the curve so
that it's not all just like all of them
the same brightness. I think having this
really cool focal point will make this
stand out. So, I'm going to go ahead and
get a mix color node. I'm going to hit
control shift D. So, duplicate the color
amp. Make sure the gradient is plugged
into it. And plug this into B. And I'm
just bring the factor over on this on
this one here. I'm going to get a hue
saturation value node.
And I'm going to bring the value down to
zero. So now we have a color ramp that's
going to mix
between a zero one with a value of zero
and the default. And we're going to use
a wave texture to make what kind of
looks like a selection of the middle
ones. So let's get a wave texture.
Let's get in a
let's plug the mapping into that. And we
need to get a color ramp.
Plug him here and plug him into the
factor so we can differentiate. So now
the wave texture is creating this. Now
if you like this effect, go nuts. Go
with it. We're actually going to go from
X to Y and it's going to create this
selection here. So I'm going to bring
the color ramp in like this.
And then I'm just going to bring that
phase to make this in the middle. So see
how it's over there? It's still a wave.
We're just sort of making the wave big
enough
so that this selection is happening
here. So I want maybe that many of the
middle. And then we can go back to the
hue sat node and bring the value up a
little bit. So now we have these middle
ones brighter than the side ones. And it
looks super cool. All right. So let's uh
let's get this let's get this animation
over with. One thing I want to do, bring
this over. I'm going to get another
mix color node and I'm going to plug
this final mix color into the factor.
I'm going to make this one up here
black, this one up here white, and then
just change the color. So, you can use
this mix node to change the color of all
these things because then you'd have to
go like into each one, make sure the
color is this is sort of your master
color. And then we can just bring that
brightness up a little bit so we can
still get our glare. And this is getting
a nice color. Something like this. All
right, let's now focus on the floor
material. Make that pretty. And we're
going to be done. So I'm going to switch
over to cycles.
And then I'm going hit this drop down
scene scene world scene lights just so
we can see what we're doing. So I'm
going to click this first plane right up
here in my outliner. I'm going to click
new. I'm going to make it metallic.
And then you can change the color just
to make sure you know. Yep. This is
affecting everything. Cool. So, what I
want to do is one, turn on my dinoiser.
So, we're going to get in a color ramp,
plug that into the roughness. We're
going to get in a voronoi texture. We're
going to hit control T, use the object
coordinate, and use color, plug that
into the color amp. So, now we're going
to get this really nice pattern. bring
random to the left and give it a scale
of 60.
And then right here, this black portion
of the color ramp represents the most
like shiny, most reflective portions of
this texture. I'm just going to bring it
up just a little bit so it's not
perfectly mirror like. And then I'm
going to bring this one down a little
bit so that everything is kind of in
that middle ground. You can see how it's
looking over there over here. Next thing
I'm going to do is I'm going to get a
bump node. plug color into height,
normal to normal. And then I'm going to
do a filter width of 1.5.
That's going to give us this nice
bumpiness that's going to affect the
light. Last thing I want to do is I'm
going to click on my wires here. I'm
going to hover over here and hit Ctrl +
C. Go back over here.
We're going to get a color ramp.
I'm going to click on the white one and
just Ctrl +V. Paste that color into
there. Color here. color of the voronoi.
Plug it into that. And then we're going
to give it a strength of like three.
I'mma hit this drop down. We're just
going to go back to our normal lights
and then bring this black portion of the
color amp in until we get enough of
these little orange pieces.
What that gives us is if I get my world
brightness to be black,
a little bit of context of, oh, there's
some still some stuff over there.
Because if I look at this in Eevee, let
me just get my normal lights. As we're
moving, those little cubes are going to
move at us. And I just think that makes
gives this a little bit more context.
I'm going to go and move my
um empty up a little bit. I want more of
these waves to be making up this scene.
So, this is what we have so far. What I
want to do is bring down the value of
a little bit more so we can mostly see
this. Another thing that's going to make
this scene look really awesome.
Let me wait till I have a flat portion.
There we go. Is click on the camera,
go over here,
and I'm going to go ahead and click on
depth of field. Bring the f-stop down
really far so we can see exactly what
it's focusing on. And then just focus on
those middle portions. And then you can
go and bring your f-stop back up till
you like how sensitive it is. You can
even at this point bring your camera in
even closer. Making sure your
the things that are out of focus are
exactly what you want. And uh we're
done. Let me go ahead and just give this
one render and see how this final output
is going to look. So here we go. This is
a the final output of this animation. It
looks really awesome. It's really
beautiful. You can have a lot of fun
with it. Let me show you the export
settings that I would recommend for this
uh 1920 x 1080 or if you want it 4K,
just type in 200. I would highly
recommend a PNG sequence. Just make a
folder, throw them in there, and then
compile that. If you don't want to do
that, you just want Blender to sped out
a video. You don't want to compile PGs,
you can go here to FFmpeg video, uh
encoding to MP4 or QuickTime. If you're
on Mac, use QuickTime. Um MP4 if you're
on a PC. and then do perceptually
lossless render render animation and
when you're done you'll have something
really cool like mine. So there you go.
That is how you create this really cool
topographic landscape inspired animation
really whatever you want to call it. Um
but that is it. Again if you want to
check out the long form video I made on
Patreon about all the different
techniques that you can do to combine
and make more animations just like this
from your own imagination, you can check
that out on Patreon. A lot of really
cool stuff packed in that video. Uh, but
with that being said, thank you guys for
watching and I'll see you in the next