How's it going, guys? So, in this
tutorial, we are going to be creating
this animation right here from start to
finish. It's going to be really fun.
This is all going to be done in the
shading. So, we're going to start off
with creating a really highly detailed,
almost woodlike looking pattern. Then,
we're going to use some masking to cut
out some of that shape so we can start
making some stuff that looks kind of
like a river. Then, we're going to use
some more shading tricks to take some of
those patterns and highlight them to
make them brighter so that they will
glow and the other ones won't glow.
After that, to create that topographic
map inspiration, we are going to be
creating a grid floor for the bottom.
Then all we're going to have to do is
animate the pattern, animate the camera,
and will be completely finished. This
animation is part of a series of
tutorials here on YouTube that are
inspired by topographic map art and
animations. I'll be posting four of
these tutorials backtoback here on
YouTube. So, if you want to learn more
of this stuff, you can go and check out
the other ones like this. They're all
really cool and there's a lot of fun
things to learn. On Patreon, I posted
what I'm calling the topographic
blueprint, which is an hour and 20
minutes of training of all the shading,
geometry nodes, and animation tricks
that are combined to make these four
animations and many others. Here on
YouTube, all those elements are combined
to make really cool animations. But on
Patreon, I'm showing you every
individual effect and tip and trick so
that you can combine them and make your
own original topographic map inspired
animations. So, if you want to check
that out, that is going to be linked in
the description and you can get a
discount if you subscribe annually. With
that being said, let's get into this
tutorial. All right, all of this is
going to be done in uh the shading. So,
what we're going to do is I'm going hit
shift A, get a plane. I'm going to hit
S10,
control A, apply that scale, and then
I'm just going to go ahead and get a
brand new window. This is going to be
the 3D viewport. This is going to be the
shader editor. I'm gonna hit N just to
move that. I'm click new. And then right
over here, we're going to go here to
Eevee. I'm gonna scroll. I'm gonna click
on the material settings. And uh I'm
going to go here from dithered to
blended. Make sure you do have a
material. And then that is going to keep
you from having grainy transparency. And
then we're just going to go here to the
EV view. And then in the uh compositing
tab up here, I'm going to click use
nodes. I'm going to type in glare and
switch this over to fog glow. So, we'll
go back to layout and now we can start.
So, here on the emission, let's give it
a strength of three for now so we can
see what's happening. And then I'm going
to hit this drop down right up here and
click on always. That's going to turn on
all of our compositing. So, world
brightness, we'll bring that down to
black. Let's get a color ramp and let's
plug that color ramp into the color and
pick our final output color. something
like a nice light blue. Something like
this. Then what I'm going to do is I'm
going to get a mix color. Plug this
here.
I'm going to make B black. And this is
just for some things that we're going to
need to do later. So let's go ahead and
plug a color ramp into A. So if we bring
factor over to the right, that's just
the black. Factor over to the B, that is
this color ramp. And let's go ahead and
add in our textures. So let's get a
noise texture.
And let's get in a wave texture.
Plug that in the vector. And then I'm
going to hit controlT. If you have the
node wrangler add-on enabled, that's
that comes with Blender by default.
You'll just hit control T or just go
ahead and get a mapping node, a texture
coordinate, and use the object
coordinate. So, let's go ahead and focus
on these guys. So, here on the scale of
the noise, don't worry about that. Bring
the scale of the wave texture really
low. I found 0.5 looks really good. And
if you bring this in, you'll notice some
things changing. We now have this. If
you bring up the scale of the noise,
it's going to add more detail here, but
we'll that'll be more obvious in a
second. Let's bring our distortion
really really high. And then our detail
scale high as well.
Something like three or four. And then
our detail. Once we bring up the detail,
we'll start to get kind of look like
what uh looks like wood.
So bring our detail to maybe 10. And
also I'm gonna switch from sign to saw.
That's just going to change it up a
little bit. So now we have this. If we
play with the phase offset, we get this
really cool looking thing. What I want
is this amount of detail. And again, if
you play with the noise texture, you
just add more and more detail into this.
So play around with that. See what you
like. I ended up settling around 13 for
my detail. Now, the reason why we added
this mix color rather than just maybe
throwing it in like that and doing this
is we need this color ramp to control
these textures here. So, we can leave it
like this. But what I want to do is I'm
going to get another color ramp and I'm
going to take this wave texture. If I
just view it, that's what it looks like
there. That's what it looks like with
both of them combined. So, what I want
to do is take just the wave texture, not
the noise, but the wave. And because it
is a larger texture, if I use it as a
way to mask out, so I'll bring this over
here to mask out parts of this larger
texture, it helps make it feel a little
bit more gives us some negative space,
but we still get to enjoy the texture.
So, what I'm going to do is I can move
it around like that. And then if we get
try testing something out here just for
fun. So you have this one moving this
way, this guy moving this way. So
everything kind of moves in that
direction. If I go ahead and I get
another node
and I make it white,
what happens is I can move this one here
and I can move this one here. So you can
move it from both sides, but you still
get that saw effect. And so you get
control of both. Or make this one white
and both of these black
and it it's going to kind of cut out
that middle. So, see that?
So, you can move this around. It's going
to cut that middle out. Now, this is not
preferable, but you can see how that
works. So, I'm just going to hit
control-z until I have both of these.
So, now we have this effect happening
right here. And you can bring it in,
crunch it in however, however much you
want. And then this detail scale is
going to have a lot of fun. So, play
with your distortion
and especially the detail scale until
you like what you see. I'm gonna go
ahead and delete one of these white uh
nodes and just keep keep it like this.
And so now we have a really really cool
scene. And again,
playing with the detail, playing with
the scale of this,
you can even play with the distortion of
the noise and you can get a lot of
stuff. So there's just a lot that you
can play with and the phase offset is
how this gets animated. Now what we can
do now is play with the fact that we
have emission strength that makes
something glow. So we have this color
amp that's creating the color. So let's
go ahead and get a map range and plug
the noise texture into the value and
then plug the result into the strength.
What I want to do is get a bring our max
color to something that is that glows.
And if you play with the from minimum,
it is going to crunch that in to just
highlight a few of these and then bring
that minimum back to reveal the rest of
the texture. So what this is going to do
is bring out
these middle lines and those are going
to be only ones that glow. So then
whenever we play with the phase offset,
so let's find a spot where it looks
really really interesting like something
over here. When we play with the offset,
we get this really interesting look
where it's not all just everything, you
know, the same brightness, right? That
would look that's just not quite as
interesting. But if you do it like this
where we use this from minimum and just
highlight a couple of these lines and
then we have the rest at that color,
you can create a really, really cool,
really interesting looking animation
with combining some textures. So now
that we have this, you can go back and,
you know, edit your texture even more to
be whatever you want it to be. So play
with this until you like what you see.
And then see the alpha. So if I go here
to scene world. So if I just go here to
the material preview, you can see it's
just a flat plane
principled BSDF with emission on top of
it. You can't see through it. And I want
to add some things to the bottom. So
what I'm going to do is I'm going to get
a color ramp. I'm going to plug this
into the alpha. And then I'm going to
plug this mix into here.
And that should show what we're looking
for. You can switch it over to constant.
And then bring this in to make sure
everything we're seeing is what we want
to see. You can switch it over here to
see. Okay. Yep. The transparency is
absolutely working. So that's what we
want. So bring it to bring your color
ramp to uh a constant and then just
crunch it all the way over there and
we're going to get transparency. So now
that we have this the animation is of
course going to come from the phase
offset just like this. It's going to be
a very sensitive phase offset. So let's
go ahead and create a grid floor beneath
it to give it that topographic map uh
like grid detail on the bottom. So,
let's just go ahead. I'm going to take
this plane. I'm going hit shift D. I'm
going to send it pretty far down. It
looks like my hit some buttons I didn't
want to hit. So, print send it far down
like that. And then if we go back here
to the view, you can see there's another
map down there. I'm going to go ahead
and just hit X. Click new. Hit the
period key and give it a strength of
like three. So, we have something down
there. Let's just scale it up.
I'm going to go ahead get my color ramp.
Let's go ahead and plug this into the
color. We're going to get a We're going
to get a voroid texture and get a dot
grid for the bottom. So, I'm just going
to hit CtrlT, get that object
coordinate, and use the distance.
Bring random to zero. I'm going to flip
my color ramp and then bring this in.
So, now we're going to have a grid of
dots going beneath it. And you can see
that parallax effect, which is what
we're looking for. And then we're going
to give ourselves a nice blue. And then
what I want to do is let's just go ahead
and I'm hit shift D and get another
plane right about there. Let's go back
to the view.
And notice you can see that parallax
effect happening. What I want to do is
I'm going to go back to the flat view.
I'm going to click this bottom one. I'm
hit shift D and then bring it up just
kind of the middle portion there. Let's
go back to the render view. And right
here where it says number three, we're
just going to click that.
And let's go ahead and go from uklitian
to chbbyev. So now we have these
squares, but let's flip that
so that we have
this this uh grid here. So I'm going to
make it a little bit bigger. I'm going
to go from linear to constant so that we
can have the thinnest lines we can get.
So something like
that. And then I'm going to bring that
strength down. I don't want it glowing.
Now notice we don't see the dots
underneath. So we just need to plug this
guy into the alpha.
And then right here in the shader, we're
going to go here from uh dithered to
blended. And then now if I make these a
little bit thicker, you can see you can
see that parallax effect um working. So
we're just going to bring this down to
be really thin.
And then maybe a little bit brighter.
And then I do want this grid to be
bigger. Maybe a scale of one.
and then make this grid
as thin as I can. There's there seems to
be a limit to how thin the grid can be,
but that's okay. So, now all I need to
do is animate my camera and animate this
texture moving to look really really
cool. So, I'm going to pick a spot of
the texture that I think is really
really interesting. And then I'm going
to go and get an empty an empty plane
axis and place it right there so I can
get my camera to look at that. So I'm
going hit shift a camera control alt0
snap it to view and then in the
constraints tab I'm going to get a
track two. I'm going to click that
empty. So now when I move my camera
it's going to stare right at the part I
want. But notice how this really cool
parallax effect is taking place. That is
the point of almost the entire point of
this tutorial is to make something
really cool with this parallax effect.
So, let's just go ahead and I'm going to
get myself maybe
400 frames.
And this won't be a looping animation.
The rare time this animation won't loop
just because it would it's okay. We not
everything needs to loop. So, I'm going
to get a key frame. Just going to click.
I'm going to stretch there. And then
just go
something like that. So, now we can look
at this.
Nice. It's really slow. The point is
just to really highlight that parallax
effect. I can even bring um the dot grid
further down. This further down the dot
grid further down just to really make
that parallax effect a lot more
dramatic. And then let's head back to
the shading and animate the phase offset
of our animation.
So, we can go here, right over here, to
the phase offset.
And it looks like this is a workspace I
haven't worked in yet. So, we're just
going to go ahead and get a
timeline.
Let's go back here. I'm just going to
hit the key frame on the phase offset
and then I'm just going to move it
around
like that.
Now,
if I go back to layout,
we can watch this animation take place.
Are we real time? It's about 14 frames a
second. So, this is a bit slower than it
will be real time. But this is how our
animation is going to look and it's
going to be really, really cool. And you
can have a lot of fun with it. Edit it,
change it, do whatever you want to it,
and it's just going to look awesome.
These uh effects just are really really
beautiful once you can play with them.
And maybe you can even go back to to
back to the shading and say maybe more
on the detail. Yeah, I think that looks
better. So now we can see a little bit
more
a little bit more interesting stuff here
on the details. But that is how this
animation is created. Let me show you
how to export it and we'll be done. So
go here to the camera icon. Actually,
sorry the the printer icon. Select your
resolution. If you want 4K, do 200. I
highly recommend using a PNG sequence
and just compiling those. Just go ahead
and choose your folder. If you want a
video instead of a PNG sequence, go to
FFmpeg video encoding to MP4 and then uh
medium quality to perceptually lossless,
and you'll be done. So, there you go.
That's how you create that. Again, if
you want to go on Patreon and check out
the full hour 20 minute video on how to
make all of these effects and combine
them and make some really cool things,
you can check that out linked in the
description. And with that being said, I
hope you enjoyed it and I'll see you in
the next