Recently, Blender Guru said that he
would not recommend beginners to learn
geometry nodes. And I completely agree
with that. But I want to go a little bit
deeper into that specific point. So what
I want to talk about is who is geometry
nodes for? Who's going to use it more
often? At what point in learning Blender
should you probably start learning
geometry nodes? And in my opinion, the
best structured way to learn that tool.
So who's geometry nodes for? It's for
everybody kind of, but in varying
degrees. So, this is a list of a lot of
the major ways that Blender is used.
Kind of most 3D applications, but
Blender specifically, this is a ton of
major uses of Blender. I ordered them
just randomly. Now, I've reordered them
in what my opinion is, who is going to
use it more often at the top all the way
to the bottom, kind of not using it much
at all. I think environment artists are
going to be using it the most. You could
build assets that can have tons and tons
of variation. And then you could take
that asset and then scatter it in tons
and tons of different variation. Right
after that, guys like me, motion
graphics artists, having the ability to
iterate really quickly, build really
interesting structures pretty fast and
make them procedural so you can change
them and having a really cool creative
approach to modeling and building and
animating is very very useful and
procedural tends to lean toward having a
lot of expressive control. Then you have
visual effects artists, modelers,
specifically prototyping because in the
prototyping stage, the model doesn't
have to be perfect, but it's to help you
get really good ideas. So having a lot
of seed values for different components
of a model so we can figure out which
direction this product is going to be is
really really useful. And the last one I
think is going to use it a lot is 3D
printing. And then after that we have
things like simulations, animation,
motion tracking and compositing and
texturing are going to be using it very
little. I think a lot of the really
basic intermediate uses of geometry
nodes, you can do those things without
geometry nodes and I would say like
older or pregeeometry nodes um tools,
which means you can get really
proficient in Blender for a long time
before you can really need to start
learning geometry nodes. Which leads me
to the next part. When should you start
learning geometry nodes if you are
someone who's probably going to benefit
from it? My simple answer is whenever
you feel comfortable in Blender and
you're making cool things without
geometry nodes. I'm a motion graphics
artist and I made several hundred
animations before Geometry Nodes was
even launched. But I will say once it
was launched and I started learning it
and getting good at it, my animations
got so much better, so much more
complex, and my ability to make really
professional animation got much better.
So if you're talking about like a hiring
standpoint, doing freelance, whatever,
my work got way better because I used
geometry nodes. So when should you start
learning it? So you're just now using
Blender and I recommend start learning
all of the big pieces of the program.
Things like the modifier system,
particles and hair systems,
polymodeling, weight paint, all of these
interesting things that all together
help you build whatever the things that
you want to build in the program. Get
pretty proficient at them. You don't
have to be a pro. You don't even have to
be like a really proficient amateur.
Just understand them and get to a point
where you're not relying on tutorials in
order to make the things that you are
coming up with in your head or wanting
to see and do from your references. I'd
say once you're at that point, I think
you will have enough knowledge to
comfortably step into using geometry
nodes. Okay. So, if you are a beginner
in geometry nodes, how would I recommend
you structure how to learn this program?
because it can be very very complicated.
Now, like I said, getting really good at
Blender and learning all of the bigger
basic tools, I think, is really
important before you start learning
geometry nodes. Mostly because I like to
look at the beginning portion of
learning geometry nodes as a way to
replace those tasks that we used to do
outside of geometry nodes that sometimes
aren't procedural. things like
displacement, face selection, boolean,
wireframe, all of those things can
actually be done within the geometry
nodes workspace, keeping them in that
same workspace. And they're all
procedural and way more powerful done
within geometry nodes rather than
outside using other tools. So with that
idea, it's a great way to structure how
you research your daily learning.
There's two ways to kind of learn
Blender. You're watching tutorials,
courses, you know, video format of
learning. You're watching someone show
you how to make a thing. And in this
case, you're watching geometry notes
tutorials. The other way, which is just
googling and researching things. So,
since we have this structure of, okay, I
want to make a wireframe or I want to do
a displacement, you'll look up how to do
displacement in geometry nodes and you
will probably go on Reddit and you will
find a screenshot of a node tree. I
think as a beginner, there's absolutely
nothing wrong with looking at a
screenshot of a node tree and going,
"Okay, let me just copy what they're
doing and then see how that works." That
is what almost everyone who's good at
geometry nodes has done at a certain
point. And even if you're doing it and
you don't know why each node does what,
still do it. I think it's very
beneficial to just get repetition going
and learning all these nodes and how
they work together. Once you do that a
bunch of times, you will start getting
it along with watching courses and
tutorials. So, with that idea of going,
okay, well, I probably will be looking
at a lot of screenshots of node trees
that I don't understand, but I'm going
to copy them and I'm going to learn how
to use them. In this video, I want to
provide a ton of those screenshots of
those basic tasks like displacement and
booleans and wireframes and all of that.
So, so let's look at how a bunch of
those tasks work and the project files I
am going to give you guys for completely
free on Patreon. You don't need a
Patreon account to download them. That's
just where it's going. You can click on
it, download the project files, and open
them up if you ever need sort of a cheat
code or, you know, a cheat list of how
to do certain things when you are
starting to learn the program. So, let
me show you how a lot of those basic
tools are made. All right, let's start
with something we all know, an array.
These nodes make an array. There's
actually a couple ways to do that in
geometry nodes, but it starts with just
a line that has five places to add an
object. And then when we plug them all
together, we get an array that allows
you to have some customizability. So
play around with all of these nodes and
see what happens. And then obviously you
can play with the object that we are
arraying as well. So this is a group of
random cubes that I have set up to show
you how booleans work. Now if I mute the
boolean, this is all of the
intersection. We have all of these
objects right here that are intersecting
together. And if looking at the
wireframe, we're going oh okay. So when
you're in a situation geometry nodes
where you have things intersecting and
you want them to boolean very simple
it's a mesh boolean node. It's going to
boolean them. It works pretty quick.
Depending on the amount of geometry in
your scene and I will also recommend I
will also recommend that booleans work
better if the objects are at varying
heights. If they're all the same height
it's not really going to work quite as
well. At least not in geometry nodes.
But this is booleans. Very common thing
to come across when you're building
things. We need to displace. This is the
set of weirdness to make displacement.
You have this multiply node to show,
hey, this is strength, which this is a
perfect way to understand math. Multiply
node if you're not familiar. Multiply
just really says the strength of the
effect either uh less or more of it. And
you can apply this to different pieces
of geometry and it will get you a noise
texture displacing the object. Extruding
is fun. And I also made it randomly
extrude with a random value node. But of
course, we have just a regular
icosphere. And then if we go ahead and
bring an extrude mesh node, it'll
extrude it however we want. And then
this fun little magic randomness node
goes, hey, randomize it. And you can
have a lot of fun with randomizing the
extrusion of whatever faces you're
dealing with in geometry nodes. Now,
insetting faces is actually kind of
weird and complicated. So, let's just do
it right now. So, you have an icosphere
and I want to insert those faces. Well,
first we're going to use an extrude mesh
node. Now, if we were to extrude it like
we did a minute ago, it's going to do
that. I'm actually going to bring the
offset to zero. So, it looks like
there's no extrusion, but there's
actually a secondary face that we
created that we can access with this
thing right here. So, what we'll do is
we'll get a scale elements node. And
right now, it's just going to scale the
entire object. I want it to only scale
that new face, the one that extruded
out. I just want to scale that. So, I'll
plug that into the selection. And now
you're seeing
this insetting happening. You can see it
right there. And if I what I want to do
is delete that face that we inset. So, I
can say only delete that secondary face
that we made. So, plug that into the
selection. And now we have some
insetting happening. So, it's kind of
weird, but geometry nodes can feel weird
quite often. And this is a great example
of just like things you just have to
rewire the way you think about building
things. Now, there's going to be a time
when you're going to wish you had a
texture coordinate system if you're
familiar with shading. So, this system
of nodes is what we just looked at in
terms of how to displace. If you need
some mapping, then you'll plug in vector
math nodes. So, in order to get them to
work, I'm going to go ahead and delete
them and get an a. We'll get vector
math. And I know I'm going to want one
stretch and squash and scale up the
texture. The other one I just want to be
able to move it around like a position.
So, we're going to get two vector math
nodes, but it's not going to work
because it needs position information.
Very easy. We need a position node. So,
plug those into each other, right into
the vector. So, this one I'm just going
to have to move on the X and the Y that
texture. And of course, is going up and
down. So, you have just this guy moving
around. You can animate. Now, I want
this one set to multiply. What he's
going to do is actually take the place
of this multiply in effectively but also
he is going to squash that texture or we
can stretch out this texture using the
multiply as well on the X Y and the Z
giving you that texture coordinate
system that you want. Now selecting
individual or groups of faces is going
to take a little bit of of of rewiring
your brain how you think of it. In
geometry nodes you can't just go into
edit mode and go I want this. I'm gonna
select this face. Select this face. You
have to do it, of course, through nodes
and accessing them. And it's learning.
Every face has a number assigned to it.
And that's called the index. So starts
at 0 and 0 1 2 3 4 5 and goes all the
way up depending on however many faces
you want. If you want to select an
individual one. So using this system of
nodes, it'll allow you to select a face.
In this case, I told it I want to select
face number 24. So I'm saying using a
math node I want to access indexes. He
just is another way of using integers
instead of that. We're selecting
different faces based on their number.
And then it has this fun little epsilon
or espelon to get the ones around it
too. So there's actually once you get
into this there's a different lots of
different ways to go about selecting
faces. This is the sort of the beginning
thought process of doing it. The very
basic singular face way of doing it. and
knowing, okay, faces have indexes,
points have indexes, all of these
indexes you'll have to be able to learn
how to access. And the last one is
something I've done over and over and
over on the channel just because
wireframes are really used quite often
in motion graphics. It's just this fun
little string of nodes. If we go ahead
and delete them all, we can look at how
it works. So, you just have an icosphere
here, and then I'm going to convert it
to curves like that. Now we need to
convert it back to a mesh and then use a
curved circle to say how wide that tube
is going to be. Now we have a wireframe.
That is all a bunch of little systems
that as a beginner you're probably going
to want to know how to do in order to
build things that you want to build. So
you can always refer back to these
project files that are on the Patreon.
Download them, open them up, or just
simply Google them. These are not
difficult processes to find on the
internet. So there you go. Hopefully
this answers the question for you.
Should I learn it? when should I learn
it if it's for me? Whatever those
questions might be. I hope this video
was beneficial for learning that. Again,
you can get that whole collection of
things on Patreon completely for free if
you want. And if you want to sign up, I
have a lot of really, really cool
exclusive content on the Patreon if you
want to check it out. So with that being
said, thank you guys for watching and I
will see you in the next