Clutter can be your absolute worst
nightmare when it comes to making really
good-looking renders. Clutter doesn't
always have to mean something bad. Quite
often, the clutter is a mix of really
cool details that I want in my design.
But sometimes you need to figure out how
to make sense of all the clutter. You
can do that by learning a system of
visual hierarchy. Sometimes you're not
putting the wrong details in your image.
They're just not organized in the best
way. and using a simple system of visual
hierarchy that can take a really
visually cluttered image and turn it
into a beautiful balanced image. So
today I want to show you a really cool
system of visual hierarchy and I'll show
you how I used it in a set of animations
that I created this week. So let's start
with what this visual hierarchy system
is. You need to take all the details
that you are going to put in your image
and divide them up into primary,
secondary, and tertiary details. Once
you're able to figure that out, you can
start to implement them and make really
balanced images. Here's what I mean.
Look at these two images. Both look
really, really cool, but one of them
just feels a little bit more balanced
and a little bit more pleasing to look
at. The one on the right has a lot of
really cool details, but the focal point
in the middle is just as visually
cluttered as the space around it, making
it feel really busy with no space to
give your eyes a break. Now, the image
on the right is just as detailed, but as
you can see, the details and the shapes
feel a little bit more intentional. You
can see we have this one large shape in
the middle, quite a few medium-sized
shapes that kind of give your eyes a
break from the busyiness, and then you
have all those really, really small
details scattered around the image as
well. One thing to look at in this
render and this render that I made is
there is a good chunk of space dedicated
to large objects that give your eyes a
place to rest. Really busy, cluttered
images can be really cool, but after a
while, they have a strain on your eyes,
and having a place for them to rest with
larger and medium-sized objects can help
you appreciate the smaller details. Now,
how can you implement the system in your
own renders? Let's look at a couple of
these renders that I just taught on
Patreon and show you how I implemented
these ideas in these because there is a
lot of details that I had to put in
them. This render here is actually a
good lesson in applying the system, but
with really, really simple use cases.
Sometimes to get a really well- balanced
scene, you just need to start simple,
just with some simple shapes. So, start
with your main idea. In this case, it's
going to be particles that take the
shape of a system of hexagons. Once you
have that idea, in this case, the
hexagons established, you can look at
your scene and try to feel out what is
missing. Here I decided if I just
duplicate the system, lower it down so
that you have a lot more details below
the main focal point and then so that
they don't draw so much attention, I
made the object smaller and the material
a little bit darker. So we still can
look at that main layer up top, but it
does show a much more full scene that
solidifies that hexagonal pattern even
more, but in a more subtle way. And then
I felt like it needed a little bit more
fun in the lighting. So, I added some
volume, added a light, and the scene
really felt completed at that point.
It's a very, very simple scene. So,
applying visual hierarchy, large object,
small object, sometimes doesn't need to
be that complicated. Now, this render
right here is a great example of having
a lot of detail in it, but we're going
to learn how to make sense of it and
make a really cool image. So, like I
said, in this image, I started with the
big objects, the medium objects, and
then all of the small details to finish
it out. Now, it could still look cool if
we just want to have large details and
small details, or we can just do medium
details and small details. Both don't
entirely look that bad, but I personally
think having a well- balanced system of
all of those details makes this image
look really cool. So, to make this, I
started in geometry nodes and modeled
the big blocks. Once I had those figured
out, I was able to give them a little
bit of wireframe detail. And then I
immediately went into adding a solid
reflective floor. After that, it made
sense to add a little bit of roughness
detail to the metallic surface that's
able to let the light interact with it
and really influence my decisions after
that. But if I like the floor and the
blocks, they still needed a lot more
detail to make the scene feel large. So
on all of the blocks, they got a subtle
voronoi detail in them. And with a tree
of wave textures and vorinoi, I was able
to add tons of small detail in the color
and the brightness of the floor, making
this really, really cool looking scene.
At this point, I had a good variety of
big details and small details, but to
balance it out, I was able to add some
smaller blocks, and immediately it felt
so much more balanced. Last thing I
added was some small emission and bump
details to the blocks, and it was
totally done. One thing you'll start to
learn as you get better at making images
is being able to look at your scene and
feel there's definitely something
missing here. But learning how to go
through that and answer that question
will really help you be more efficient
in making really beautiful images. Now,
I want to lightening round a few of
these renders and talk about these as
well. The initial idea was to make this
hologram style looking city in this
animation, but at this point it just
felt really cluttered. I didn't entirely
know what to do and I landed on using a
voronoid pattern to cut lots of gaps in
the city and actually makes it look a
little bit more interesting. Gives the
scene some room to breathe. And I was
able to add some smaller dot details and
some other things in there to make the
scene feel really nice and and broke up
that scene that kind of looked like an
aerial view of New York and just made it
feel a little bit more balanced and
breathable. The point of this scene was
to teach how to use curves and make them
kind of look a little bit more sci-fi
and use voroi to manipulate them. But I
wanted the scene to look really nice and
balanced. So I started with the small
curves and made a lot of them, broke
them up a little bit and added some
light to them. And then I added a few
details on the floor with that square
looking voronoi pattern. But to me there
was something missing. And the answer to
that was a very large set of curves as
well on top of them to really balance
out this scene and make it look really
beautiful. And I absolutely love this.
It's a great wallpaper. It's a great
asset for a larger scale environment.
It's really, really cool. So, there you
have it. Hopefully, this helps you
understand some visual hierarchy. And
like I mentioned, all these animations I
talked about are available right now on
Patreon and you can learn them all. And
this animation specifically, I will be
posting on YouTube here for free in
about a week or so. So, you can
subscribe and look out for that. But
with that being said, thank you guys for
watching. I hope you learned something.
I hope this helps you elevate your own
work and make some really cool designs
that you're really proud of. And I'll
see you guys in the next