How's it going? So, you may have seen
this effect uh somewhere on the
internet. And if you don't know what
it's called, it's called blob tracking.
And typically, it's made in touch
designer. But if you don't know how to
use touch designer or don't want to pay
for it, I'm going to show you how to get
this effect completely free in Blender.
There's four main steps to be able to
achieve this look. First thing we're
going to do is create some geometry
that's going to have variation in
geometry size, which is going to
correlate to the effect in the shading.
Next, we're going to use an attribute to
turn the geometry into a texture that we
can use in the shader editor and use
that to kind of displace and glitch
around the image that we're using.
Because this effect is created with
geometry, we can actually take geometry,
convert it, and have them all connect
with curves. Then all we have to do is
take the one noise texture that is
creating all of these movements, animate
it, and you're completely done. So, it
is just as simple as that. If you don't
know about the videos on my channel,
I've started a series of After Effects
or kind of 2D style animations here on
YouTube. So, you can check out several
of those along with my Patreon where you
can get a lot of extra content. Almost
every month, I'm releasing a new batch
of tutorials and I'm always on there and
releasing new things. So, if you want to
check it out, it's linked in the
description and you can get a discount
if you subscribe annually. Now, let's
get into this tutorial. All right, so
let's start with step number one. and
we're going to go ahead and hit shift A
and throw a plane or any piece of
geometry into the main workspace. I'm
going to be using Blender
4.4.1. We're just going to open up a new
window. Switch this one over to the
geometry nodes editor. I'm going to hit
in and then we're going to get a new
geometry nodes tree. Let's go ahead and
delete the group input. And we're going
to go ahead and get in
a
grid. Also, I'm going to hit the tilt
key over here, go to the top, and we're
going to go and get our camera. And then
I'm just going to bring it out. I'm
really doing this just visually to fit
the geometry to a 16x9 space, which is
what it's created by default. So I'm
going to go ahead with the grid and just
kind of eyeball it. This does not need
to be exact. This is just sort of an
artistic approach to this. So exact
measurements really are not necessary.
I'm going to go over here to the
wireframe view. And right now we just
have four faces. Right now we just have
four faces here. So what I'm going to do
is just get them to be get them to be
relatively square. So, we're going to do
six by four. And this is the first set.
And just imagine that when the image is
going to be spread across, these squares
are going to be where those glitchy
points go. So, depending on how small or
large you want those images to be,
that's going to correspond with the size
of your faces. Now, what we're going to
do is get a separate geometry node and
switch this over to separate faces.
We're going to get a join geometry node
and then plug in the invert. And what
we're going to do is plug a texture into
this to tell it where and how much to
separate this geometry. If that doesn't
make any sense, um, just follow along
and it will make sense. So, we're going
to go ahead and get in a noise texture.
We're going to plug the factor into the
selection and nothing's going to happen
just mainly because the noise texture is
not dramatic enough. So, we're going to
get in a color ramp to force that. If we
switch this over to linear to constant
and then just bring the white one in the
middle and you can do 0.5 to make it
perfectly in the middle. Now this is set
up. You'll notice if we just get a
subdivide mesh node and throw it right
here. It's now going to take some of the
separated geometry and subdivide it. So
if you bring this over here, you can get
more or less subdivision in the
geometry. So now I'm going to take the
portion of the geometry that is
subdivided. This line right here. We're
going to do another separate geometry.
So really, we're only going to be
dealing with the geometry that makes up
the portions that are subdivided. And
we're just going to plug it right there.
And then we're going to do the same
thing. Plug the noise texture, the color
ramp, just plug those right into the
selection. Plug the inverted into join
geometry. And then plug a subdivision or
subdivide mesh node there. And now we're
going to
have this interesting set. So if you
switch this noise texture to 4D, you can
actually animate how this looks. I'm
going to bring the detail to zero just
so it's a cleaner look. And now you can
animate this subdivision look. I forget
the specific way to describe this style,
but that's how you achieve it. You
essentially do two sets of separation or
as many sets of separation as you want
to get a really really interesting set.
Now that we have this, the point of
creating this in geometry is to be able
to convert it into a texture, but to be
able to go back and actually use the
geometry that we are turning into a
texture. So it all is created from the
same set of data. So what we can do now
is get a store named attribute node. I'm
just going to give it any name I want.
I'm going to do R just to represent that
it's random. And then we're going to
plug the color ramp. We're going to plug
the noise texture straight into the
value socket. And then we're going to
tell it make we're going to tell it to
recognize the faces. So now we're able
to throw this information into the
shading and look at it like a texture.
So, what we'll do is get a set material
node. Go right over here and just create
a material and grab it right there. And
I'm going to switch over to the shading
tab. So, I'm just going to go ahead and
rearrange these windows really quickly.
I should just save these, but I just I
just never get around to it. Um, and
we're going to go here to the shader
editor. Now, what we want to do is go
ahead and call that attribute that we
created with the store named attribute
node. That's going to just be an
attribute node.
uh call the name which was R and plug
factor into base color. And now we can
see that texture. So if I were to go
back to geometry nodes and go to the
material preview window, I can play with
the W. And you'll notice we have
essentially a black and white texture
that we can uh play around with. So I'm
going to go back to the shading and
let's go ahead and put our image into
this scene. So go ahead and pick any
image or video that you want. either
images and videos, it will behave the
same in terms of this glitching effect.
So, what I'm going to do is if you have
the node wrangler add-on enabled, just
hit control T. It's going to give you a
quick mapping setup. Use the object
coordinate and I'm going to click open
and grab my image. You can see a couple
of these images that I was playing with.
I found these landscape images to look
really nice. And then I'm going to go
get an empty and use that as uh the
object that creates kind of my texture
coordinate or my mapping. So, if you
click the empty, then you can click the
empty here in the viewport and scale it
up. Now, the image is uh squished. It's
kind of a square. So, you can take your
empty and just sort of stretch it out.
Kind of eyeball it. Um I should just
look at the original image, but I'm just
going to go by memory of how I remember
it looking. And then one quick thing, go
ahead and just delete the principled and
plug the image straight into the
surface. And that's going to bring it
back to sort of the images original
color and contrast and all that. So it's
not a surface. So you can just go ahead
and scale up the image to fit whatever
square. I'm using a 16x9
um ratio here. And this is now our
image. Now what we can do is right here
on this line get a mix
color. And now throw that texture or
that geometry straight into there. And
you're going to notice that glitch start
to happen. So it's starting to move it
around. It's combining your regular
mapping with this new black and white
value mapping. And it's going to kind of
play with it a little bit. And so we can
head back to geometry nodes. I'm going
collapse this window here. Notice there
is a line going straight into the store
named attribute. So what we can do is
get a color ramp to play with that a
little bit. So, if you get a color ramp,
switch it to
constant, you'll be able to just get a
couple, say something like like this.
And then I'm going to go back to the
empty and get that background image to
be scaled properly. There we go. And
then if you play with the W, we now have
this
image glitching around. And it's pretty
cool. What I found looks really good is
if you get a wave texture with a scale
of
0.5,
it makes the images feel a little bit
better. We're going to do a scale of two
on the noise texture. And it does I do
appreciate the behavior a little bit
more. So, I'm going to flip my color
ramp
actually. And I noticed when I flipped
the color ramp, he used the combination
with the wave. I really do enjoy that
movement quite a bit more than the
original. Um, but really it's going to
be up to just playing with it. You can
just keep the noise texture, play with
those values. Um, but this I really,
really like. So, now that we have
this working properly, we now need to
create that effect where all of those
little squares have this red line
connecting to each other.
So, we're going to go back to the
wireframe view. And what I'm going to do
is I'm just going to go ahead and sever
the connection right there. And we're
going to go ahead and get
a delete geometry. And I'm going to plug
the the color amp right here that plugs
into the store named attribute. This
color amp is the one that crunches in
those images to just a couple of those
cubes, a couple of those squares that
glitch in and out. So I want to use that
same specification to be plugged into
the delete geometry. So we can actually
delete that specific geometry. So what
I'm going to do is plug this join
geometry, the one that goes right before
the store named attribute right after
all of these nodes that created that
variation geometry. Plug that into the
geometry. Switch this over to face.
We're going to plug the color ramp into
that and then plug and then we're going
to get
a join geometry so that we can plug this
stuff that all this this image
information into it and this new
information. So we'll just plug that
there. Plug this
here and you'll
notice we'll play with the W. It's doing
that. You'll notice it's doing that.
What we can do is just invert it with a
color ramp.
So plug that there and then just flip
the color ramp. So that's just inverting
that texture so we don't have to change
anything. And then now you have all of
this geometry. What I want to do is
convert all of these faces into uh
points. So I'm just going to take these
guys here, highlight them, and bring
them over a little bit. What I want to
do is to turn these faces into points.
And so that's very easy. You can just go
ahead and do a mesh to points and say
use the faces. And so now again, if you
play with that noise texture, we're just
getting points. And if I were to plug
this material set material into the
join, you'll
notice, see those points are on top of
each image square. So this is sort this
is just to confirm, hey, this is working
properly. And once these points connect,
this effect is going to work, right? So,
I'm just going to go ahead and sever
that and go back. What we need to do now
is to create a really kind of weird
setup of nodes to get every point here
to connect. So, I'm just going to go
ahead and play with my W till I have a
few more points that we'll want to
connect. So, right after the mesh to
points node, let's go ahead and get a
for each element
node. And we're going to need two of
them. So, let's go ahead. I'm g sever
that points to geometry. And then this
lower green. Plug him there. And then
we're just going to get another for each
element node. And we're going to plug
this lower green into hem right there.
And here's what we're going to do now.
Let's go ahead and throw some data into
it to get all of those points to connect
each other with a curve. So, first we're
going to need a position node. And
because it's a for each element node,
once we plug him into here, it's going
to create a position some position data
for each one of those points that we
generated. Let's go ahead and get a
curve line node. Curve line. And the
this point we're going to get the
position of each point into the start of
the curve line. So one end of the curve,
we're saying, hey, start there. Now, we
need to get the other end of the curve
to also connect to everything. So, I'm
just going to go ahead and give myself a
little bit more space. I'm highlighting
and hitting G. Now, we're going to need
to get a
sample index node. We're going to get
another position node. We're going to
switch this over to a vector. Plug
position into value. The mesh to points
is going to go here, right here into the
geometry. And then the element right
here into the geometry. And then he is
going to represent the end of the curve.
And then we're just going to plug this
curve line into geometry. And now all of
them connect. So it's kind of a weird
convoluted mess of nodes. If you
recognize the setup, I actually did a
tutorial on it earlier and it created
this animation. So that very much goes
to show same process, highly different
result, similar idea. So you can really
take really cool things like this and
use them for other things. And that's
where you can start to take these
processes and go, "Oh, I recognize that
all these things are connected. I
recognize that node setup. I'm going to
use it in this completely different way.
And that's how you can really creatively
use setups like this that are very
technical, but you can be very artistic
with their use case. Now that we have
all these connected, there's some stuff
going on that may not be entirely
visual. But
essentially, you may see one curve.
There's really, I believe, three. One
going there, one going back, one going
back. So, you have some duplicates
that's going to create extra geometry.
So, I want to just go ahead and delete
the curves that are overlapping because
you can't even see it. And once we turn
it into geometry, it's going to be three
times the geometry we need. So what
we'll do is convert it to a
mesh. We'll do a curve to mesh. And this
isn't to create that wireframe effect
that I'm normally doing with this node.
It's simply to turn it into a
mesh and allow us to use this merge by
distance. And what that's going to do is
just kill that duplicate curve. You
couldn't see it visually, but in the
data you would be able to recognize
that. This just serves to delete the
redundant curve. Now, what I'm going to
do is get in a mesh to
curve and then a curve to
mesh. And then you get a curve
circle. Feel like I say this every time,
but we've done this a thousand times on
the channel. We're creating a wireframe.
And you just plug that there. And now we
bring that radius down. You now have
this. So, what we can do is take this
set
material node and just plug that into
the join geometry. And we're back. If
you want to kind of just appreciate it
and see it, you can play with that noise
texture. And now there's a curve.
There's a line connected to each one of
those image cubes. So, I'm going to go
back here to the uh circle curve and I'm
just going to bring it pretty far down.
Something like that. And the resolution
of four is really all you're going to
need cuz it's going to be extremely
thin. geometry isn't going to be very
noticeable. Now it's white. It's just
white by default. What you can do is get
a set material node. Go over here. Click
new. We're going to switch it over to an
emission node and just make it a nice
red. And then just go ahead and grab
that red right there. And now we have
these red lines. I'm going to go say
maybe 05 might be good. I would even go
even
uh thinner on this. And then we need one
more thing. I want to have these little
cubes, um, these little planes at each
connection. So, what I'm going to do is
right here on the node that says mesh to
points. What I'm going to
do, we're going to get an instance on
points
node and just plug him into the points.
Plug him into the join
geometry and get a
grid. And you're not going to see
anything. It needs to be we're going to
get a transform geometry node just to
kind of bring it up a slight bit so that
we can see it. And then you can just go
also put that same
material on that. So now we have the
finished effect. If you go back to sort
of the master
noise, you can now see and appreciate
this effect. And all we need to do is
animate it. Uh because we kind of I like
to go the extra mile and loop the
animation. We're going to loop the W and
the noise. And so we have our timeline
down here. I'm going to stick with 250
frames. That's going to give you about I
think a 10-second animation if I'm
remembering right. And so I'm going to
go ahead and bring my W to zero. I'm
going to duplicate the noise. Get a mix
color node. Mix color node. And plug
factor there. And bring the factor over
to the left. So right here on the W, you
hit I to add a key frame. Hit I on the
factor. And then we're going to go to
the very end. And I'm going to say
probably a value of
five. And then we're going to slide this
guy over and hit I. Hit I. Now that
we're at the very end of the animation,
hit your W. He should be zero. Go back
to frame zero and do
five. And there we go. Now we used a
value of five and neg 5. If you want it
faster, do like 10 negative 10. If you
want it slower, do
like.5gative.5. You kind of get the
idea. But your values are going to
create the speed of the animation. So,
that's really going to dictate um how it
looks. I would render this in the Eevee
render engine. I think I'm in cycles
right now. Yeah. Just switch over to
Eevee. Press play. And you now have a
really, really cool finished interesting
looking touch designer effect. Um, and
all points connect to all points. It's
really cool. It's pretty useful. Um,
especially just having some fun and
glitching some things around. So, there
you go. That is the full animation. You
can get the project file right now on my
Patreon. You can check that out linked
in the description. Hopefully you
learned something and I'll see you guys
in the next tutorial.