All right, here's the scenario. You've
been watching tutorials for 1, two,
maybe three or more years, and now they
just don't seem to be challenging to you
anymore, or just aren't quite as
interesting as they used to feel. And
now you're at a place where you're just
not progressing anymore. You know that
there's a lot more to learn, but you
can't find it, and tutorials just aren't
offering the things that scratch your
itch. I have found myself in that
position before and I want to show you a
technique that I did all of 2024 and it
really improved my work and my craft so
much. First, I think it's important to
understand how this happens if we're
able to understand it and move past it.
At their core, tutorials offer problems
and solutions in a single piece of
content, which allows you to go from
being reliant on tutorials to be able to
make anything to being able to remember
all that stuff and make things that you
come up with yourself. Now, problems
that tutorials solve or say, hey, this
is a design, an environment, whatever.
I'm going to show you how to make it.
You don't know how to make it. This
video will show you that. Or say, hey, I
don't know how to make a cloth
simulation. That's the problem. the
video will solve it. Now, after a couple
years of doing this, those tutorials
just stop being useful. You stop really
needing the ones that keep getting
uploaded or the ones that have existed
for a long time. And that's exactly what
had been happening to me for quite a
while. And I felt stagnant. I felt like
I wasn't learning anything new yet. I
saw a lot of work that I didn't know how
to do. And I knew there was things to
learn, but I was too reliant on YouTube
tutorials and courses. So, how did I
move past this? I did thematic studies
of large groups of work with the goal of
studying them enough to find things that
I don't know how to do. First, I have to
pick a topic. I have to collect the
inspiration on that topic. Then, I have
to start looking at those images and
videos and start getting challenged. The
goal here is to make a lot of project
files. You don't have to finish them,
but find things that really challenge
you. Then after a lot of R&D, distill
all of this work into five really cool
images that feel like they fit within
the work that you collected for this
project. Now, I mentioned I did this all
of 2024. There were a ton of videos that
I uploaded that year that were
breakdowns of projects. Those projects
came from those self-appointed research
and development sprints that I did. I
would make those boards and really study
them and they would challenge me. I'm
going to use this video as an example to
show you how I did all that. This video
was called the power of curves and this
was a product of learning really cool
things. I wanted to see how far I can
take using geometry nodes with curves to
make really beautiful animations. So,
first I collected a Pinterest boards of
just images that I thought were cool.
Don't pick images that you think you
know how to do. Just pick images that
you think are cool cuz that will lead
you to roadblocks. Let's take this
animation for example. I wanted to make
something that kind of looked like an
eyeball of curves. So, the first thing I
didn't know how to do was how to array
all of those curves in a circular
pattern and have them point outward. So,
that was a rabbit hole that I had to go
down to to learn how to basically point
things out based on the normal. Then, I
had to figure out how to displace them
properly, how to get those curves to
actually move in a way that I wanted and
controlled. And I didn't understand how
to do that. That was more research that
I had to do. Then I had to learn how to
get light to properly move up and down
these curves and how to randomly place
those lights. So, not all the curves had
those moving lights on them. All of
those things were things I did not know
how to do. I had to go through Blender
subreddits and forums and a lot of hair
pulling to figure these things out and
it resulted in one of my absolute
favorite animations I've ever done.
Another really cool and kind of simple
problem solving was I found this image
and I wanted to make something similar
to it. So my first task was was to take
curves and have smaller and smaller
smaller ones moving inwards first to be
able to displace them. I did not know
how to do that in geometry nodes which
led me to figuring out how to use
simulation nodes in a very simple way to
get them to sort of array inward. And
then all I had to do was displace them
and figure out some things that I
already knew how to do. But it it taught
me how to use a really simple tool which
is the simulation nodes very
primitively. Now this one I was really
inspired by. I wanted to figure out how
to take a big sort of array of curves
and just sort of like make them move
around uh kind of like something you
would see in the ocean. So, first
because I figured out how to use
simulation nodes to create an array, I
created an array of those curves, then I
was able to displace these guys. But the
problem was the bottoms of them were
moving with the displacement, which
meant I had to figure out how to isolate
the displacement only to the top
portion, which led me to figuring out
how to use position information to
isolate the bottom to keep it still and
have the top only move and have some
control. That took a little bit of R&D
on my end to understand vector math,
understand position, and how to mix
things together in order to get that to
look nice. Now, I did this multiple
times and I'm even working on the next
one, which is all about recreating
really cool sci-fi looking things. And
there will be a lot of things that I
learned from that that will turn into
tutorials that I put on this channel.
So, it not only benefits me personally,
it benefits the YouTube channel. It
benefits the Patreon because all of
these projects I ended up putting on
Patreon. And like I said, I'm distilling
I'm creating five or so images from each
one and those turn into tutorials for
everything that I'm doing. So, for me
personally, it's been a huge huge
benefit. and you as an artist doing
whatever you want to do with your art. I
also think it is going to be a huge huge
benefit to do these kind of sprints. So
to summarize this process, it goes to
picking a topic, collecting inspiration
on that topic. Get as much as you can,
then start diving into the things that
you think are interesting and start
getting challenged and make a lot of
different project files. Then once
you've gone through the ringer of
research and Reddits and YouTubes and
all of the hair pulling frustration of
learning things you don't know how to
do, distill those into five really cool
designs that you can be proud of and put
on your portfolio, your Instagram, your
own work, doing whatever you want. I
would recommend doing that once a month.
And I'm still doing that. All of my
processes like this, they end up as full
collections on my Patreon if you want to
check that out. My Patreon is linked in
the description. And every single month
I've been putting out these projects of
really learning things and giving
everyone those new topics. But it
doesn't all stay on Patreon. The YouTube
channel is also being populated with all
of these research and development
projects, too. So, you can get that
stuff on Patreon and you can get it here
on YouTube. If you want to check out the
Patreon, you can get a discount if you
subscribe annually. But enough of that.
Hopefully, you got something really cool
from this. Hopefully, you can really
progress and move past feeling like
you're in a stagnant rut. If you can
relate to that. And uh with that being
said, thank you guys for watching and I
will see you in the next one.